<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A rational, compendious way to convince, without any dispute, all persons whatsoever, dissenting from the true religion. By J.K.</title>
            <author>Keynes, John, 1625?-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47321</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K393</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200380</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825062</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825062</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29434</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47321)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29434)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2188:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A rational, compendious way to convince, without any dispute, all persons whatsoever, dissenting from the true religion. By J.K.</title>
                  <author>Keynes, John, 1625?-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30], 124 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J.K. = John Keynes.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29434:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RATIONAL, Compendious way TO CONVINCE, Without any DISPUTE, All
Perſons whatſoever, Diſſenting from the TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E RELIGION.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. K.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. IV. 7.</bibl> 
               <p>Signatum eſt ſuper nos lumen vultus tui, Domine.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:29434:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29434:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE variety of Sects, which daily ſwarm here in
<hi>England,</hi> has forced me upon <hi>this way</hi> of ending
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies in Religion. No body can confute <hi>in particular</hi> the
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Tenets of each Sect, unleſs he be firſt well informed <hi>what they
are:</hi> and our Sects are ſo <hi>nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,</hi> and ſo <hi>various,</hi>
that to be well informed of the <hi>particular Tenets</hi> of each one of them,
a mans life is not ſufficient. Yea, even Thoſe, who do profeſs to be all
oſ <hi>the ſame</hi> Religion, are many times <hi>ſo different</hi> one
from <pb facs="tcp:29434:3"/>another, that we can ſcarce find Two among them, who do
perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agree in the <hi>Articles of their Faith.</hi> Several Religions
retain only <hi>the name</hi> of what they were when firſt broached; and
ſhould one be perfectly acquainted with the proper Tenets of the Sects which
<hi>are now in Vogue,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a ſhort time he would be to ſeek; when
<hi>other new Hereſies</hi> come into faſhion. Beſides, it is one thing
to convince a man, that he is <hi>in a wrong way,</hi> which we may do by
refuting the <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Errors</hi> of the Religion he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes; and
another thing to ſhew him <hi>which is the True way:</hi> which cannot be
done, but by <hi>demonſtrating</hi> unto him the True Religion.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I have endeavoured, <pb facs="tcp:29434:3"/>without taking notice of
the <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Errors</hi> of each Sect, to find out a <hi>Method,</hi>
whereby to evidence, <hi>to all perſons what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,</hi> the True
Religion. For, this being once <hi>evidenced unto them,</hi> whoever ſtrayes
from it, may clearly ſee, not only that he is <hi>in the wrong,</hi> but
alſo how he may put himſelf <hi>in the right</hi>-Certain it is, that if
there be a <hi>True Religion</hi> in the world (as we ſhall evince there is)
it may be found out by all ſuch as are <hi>concerned therein;</hi> and
conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently by <hi>all perſons</hi> whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; For they are <hi>all
concern'd</hi> in finding out the True Religion; ſince they are all
<hi>bound</hi> to ſave their Souls: Nor can they <hi>ſave their Souls,</hi>
unleſs they <hi>pleaſe God;</hi> nor pleaſe God, unleſs they 
<pb facs="tcp:29434:4"/>
               <hi>embrace the True Religion:</hi> which is only able to teach
them, what they are to do to pleaſe God. (<hi>Sine Fide impoſſibile
eſt, placere Deo,</hi> Heb. 11.6.) Nor finally embrace the True Religion,
unleſs they can find out, and be convinced <hi>which it is.</hi> And if all
perſons whatſoever may <hi>find out,</hi> which the True Religion is, there
muſt needs be <hi>ſome way,</hi> whereby they may find it out: and this way
alſo muſt be ſuch, that it <hi>may be found out.</hi> For what matters
it, that there be a way to find out ſuch a thing, if no Body can find out
<hi>which that way is?</hi> My endeavour therefore was to find out This way,
<hi>of Convincing all perſons whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,</hi> concerning the True
Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:29434:4"/>Now <hi>Natural Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Experience</hi>
teaches us, that it is not poſſible to convince any one <hi>by
diſcourſe,</hi> but out of what <hi>the perſon,</hi> with whom we deal,
<hi>does admit.</hi> For all conviction by diſcourſe muſt be <hi>grounded
upon premiſes:</hi> and nothing can be convinced, or concluded out of
premiſes, <hi>unleſs they be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> If every Thing is <hi>to be
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> we ſhall never <hi>finiſh the proof</hi> of any Thing. The
art there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of convincing a perſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in diſcovering
<hi>ſuch premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes granted by him,</hi> whence is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred what we pretend
to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince him of,</p>
            <p>And if the premiſes be not only <hi>granted</hi> by our
Adverſary, but alſo <hi>True in themſelves,</hi> they may be effectual,
both to <pb facs="tcp:29434:5"/>convince our <hi>Adverſary,</hi> and evince <hi>the
Truth</hi> too. But if they be not <hi>True</hi> in themſelves, yet granted
to be ſo, they may <hi>convince him,</hi> but can never <hi>evince the
Truth:</hi> And ſuch Arguments are commenly ſtiled <hi>Argumenta ad
hominem.</hi> Since therefore my deſign was, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to convince <hi>the
perſons,</hi> but to evince <hi>the Truth</hi> alſo, and to convince
<hi>all perſons whatſoever,</hi> concerning the True Religion, I further
reſolved, to ſeek out Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples <hi>True</hi> in themſelves,
<hi>perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent</hi> to prove the intent, and ſuch as <hi>no perſon
whatſoever</hi> could deny, or queſtion.</p>
            <p>But where ſhall we meet with <hi>ſuch Principles?</hi>
eſpecially ſince we live in an Age, wherein a <hi>good wit,</hi> and a
<hi>bold wit</hi> are <pb facs="tcp:29434:5"/>accounted <hi>Synonima's;</hi> and thoſe
are held to be <hi>moſt ingenious,</hi> who can <hi>deny moſt.</hi> If we
apply our ſelves to the ſeveral <hi>Writers</hi> of each reſpective Sect,
thinking to convince the profeſſors of ſuch Sects by the
<hi>Teſtimonies</hi> of their own <hi>Doctors,</hi> we ſhall find, that
ſome Fancy <hi>one Author,</hi> ſome <hi>another;</hi> though they all
profeſs themſelves to be of the <hi>ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> Neither will
they ſtand <hi>to all</hi> the Author, whom they Fancy, <hi>aſſerts;</hi>
but to what they pleaſe only, and in what ſenſe too they pleaſe to
<hi>interpret</hi> it. Yea; though they promiſe many times, at the Beginning,
to ſtick to what <hi>ſuch a Doctor,</hi> to whom they are devoted, does
affirm, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to <hi>ſuch a Debate;</hi> yet when they are preſs'd,
they flie off, <pb facs="tcp:29434:6"/>and ſay, That <hi>they will not pin their Faith
upon the ſleeve of</hi> Luther, Calvin, <hi>or any other particular Doctor of
the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we make our addreſs to the <hi>ancient Fathers</hi> of the
Church, endeavouring to evidence, by their Teſtimonies, <hi>the Truth</hi> of
ours, and the <hi>Falſhood</hi> of our Adverſaries Religion, <hi>this
To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick</hi> is obnoxious to <hi>the ſame flaws,</hi> as the former. For our
Adverſaries admit, among the ancient Fathers, <hi>only whom they fancy,</hi>
and of him <hi>only what</hi> they fancy, and this only <hi>in what
ſenſe</hi> they fancy: and though, to amuſe the people, they often
vapour, that the Fathers, for <hi>the firſt 600 years</hi> after Chriſt,
did ſtand for them, yet <pb facs="tcp:29434:6"/>when they are pinched with <hi>clear
Teſtimonies</hi> produced out of them, deſtructive to their <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
Sentiments,</hi> they plainly confeſs, that even the chiefeſt of the
ancient Fathers were infected with <hi>Non-fundamental Errors,</hi> (and
<hi>ſuch Errors</hi> only they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe to <hi>Bellarmin</hi> and other
Writers of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church) and with ſeveral
<hi>Superſtitions</hi> of Popery: or they come to ſlight them all, ſaying
with ſome <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Lutherans,</hi> that one <hi>Kem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitius</hi> is worth a
thouſand <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtins,</hi> or (with their grand Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch
<hi>Luther</hi>) that they do not value a <hi>Thouſand Cyprians,</hi> a
<hi>Thouſand Auſtins;</hi> nay, nor the <hi>whole Univerſal Church,</hi>
worth a ſtraw. The ſame may be ſaid of <hi>Tradition.</hi> For they admit
<pb facs="tcp:29434:7"/>the Tradition only of <hi>ſuch men,</hi> and in <hi>ſuch
matters,</hi> as they think fit; or when they are urged, they ſlight it.</p>
            <p>If we appeal to the <hi>General Councils</hi> of the Church,
ſhewing that by <hi>their Canons</hi> our Tenets are
<hi>eſtabliſhed,</hi> and the Errors of our Adverſaries
<hi>condemned;</hi> of <hi>eighteen General Councils,</hi> they admit only
<hi>four:</hi> Nay, they do not afford any <hi>abſolute aſſent</hi> to
the Definitions of any Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council whatſoever, but only a
<hi>conditional,</hi> viz. as far only as they, guided by their <hi>own
pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Spirit,</hi> do judge, that what the Council defines, is <hi>agreeable
to Scripture.</hi> And ſure; they will not deny <hi>ſuch an
aſſent,</hi> even to what the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> has defined.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:29434:7"/>If we betake our Selves to Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, producing
thence many <hi>pregnant proofs</hi> in vindication of the Articles we defend
in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to <hi>the Proteſtant</hi> Church, though Sectaries boaſt
that Scripture is on their ſide, yet they allow only of <hi>ſuch
Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> of <hi>ſuch Verſions,</hi> and of <hi>ſuch an
Interpretation,</hi> as their <hi>private Spirit</hi> dictates unto them: So
that if we will prove out of Scripture, as out of a <hi>principle admitted</hi>
by our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, the Articles of our Faith, we muſt prove them out of
Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, as <hi>interpreted</hi> according to their <hi>private Spirit;</hi>
which is impoſſible. For how can it be poſſible to evince againſt a
<hi>Zuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glian,</hi> for example, out of that place of Scripture, Matth. 26. 
<pb facs="tcp:29434:8"/>
               <hi>This is my body,</hi> the Real Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt in the
Euchariſt, if we muſt take that place <hi>in the ſenſe</hi> of a
Zuinglian, <hi>viz.</hi> in a <hi>meer Figurative ſenſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſince Sectaries will not aſſent to any thing in matters
of Religion, aſſerted by <hi>Doctors, Fathers, Tradition,</hi> or
<hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils,</hi> further then it is <hi>agreeable</hi> to Scripture; neither
will they <hi>aſſent to Scripture,</hi> but as <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted</hi> by
their own <hi>private ſpirit,</hi> it follows manif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtly, that the malice of our Aduerſaries has rendred
all the forementioned <hi>Topicks</hi> (though <hi>good in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi>)
as admitted by them, and <hi>in the manner</hi> they admit them,
<hi>inſignificant,</hi> and <hi>ineffectual</hi> to prove out of them, as out
of <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes granted</hi> by our Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <pb facs="tcp:29434:8"/>the Tenets
of the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and that whoever makes uſe of them <hi>as of
ſuch,</hi> will of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten be at a loſs. Yea, what ſhall we ſay to <hi>Les
beaux Eſprits</hi> of our Nation, (the Spawn of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie) who openly
diſavow <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, Fathers, Tradition, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils,</hi> and
<hi>Scripture?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore to the end we may argue well againſt our Adverſary,
out of a <hi>Principle</hi> as granted by him; it is not enough, that ſuch a
principle be <hi>good,</hi> and <hi>perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent</hi> in it ſelf: but it is
neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, that it be <hi>granted</hi> by our Adverſary, and in
<hi>ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> as that it may be <hi>effectual</hi> to evince what
we intend.</p>
            <p>If, finally we retreat to <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Reaſon,</hi> endeavouring
thereby to make out the True Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; <pb facs="tcp:29434:9"/>though there be no
rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal man, who will plainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that he renounces <hi>all Natural
Reaſon,</hi> (for ſo he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the being a <hi>Rational man,</hi>
yea ſuch as diſallow <hi>all other Topicks,</hi> do moſt vapour of
<hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Reaſon</hi>) yet many confine it, in ſeveral matters, to their
own <hi>private Notions,</hi> and <hi>Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding, there are ſome Principles ſo
<hi>manifeſt,</hi> and ſo <hi>general,</hi> that no man whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever can
<hi>deny,</hi> or <hi>queſtion</hi> them, without evidently rendring
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf uncapable of conferring with any rational man. Such is this
Principle, <hi>SOMETHING IS TRUE,</hi> which no <hi>Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptique,</hi> though
never ſo Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant, can call in queſtion; <pb facs="tcp:29434:9"/>and whoever
ſhould affirm, that <hi>NOTHING IS TRUE,</hi> would not only incapacitate
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>for all humane converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> but alſo grant <hi>the
very thing</hi> he denies: This Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Nothing is True,</hi> being
of the nature of ſuch, as <hi>falſifie themſelves,</hi> and cut their own
throats. Nay, if <hi>nothing be true,</hi> the Poſition our Adverſaries
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to maintain is <hi>not True,</hi> viz. That <hi>the Roman Church is
infected with Errors, and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our preſent Method therefore is bottom'd upon the forementioned
Principle, <hi>Something is true;</hi> which I keep in reſerve, to the end,
that in caſe <hi>other Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> ſhould fail me, I might have
wherein to truſt, and whereon to <pb facs="tcp:29434:10"/>ground the Conviction of
<hi>all Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters whatſoever</hi> from the true Religion. For <hi>this
Principle</hi> being once agreed unto (as <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily</hi> it muſt
be) I deduce thence the truth not only of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholique
Religion, but alſo of <hi>whatſoever</hi> ſhe delivers as an
<hi>Article</hi> of <hi>Divine</hi> Faith.</p>
            <p>This Method is <hi>Rational, Compendious, Clear, Eaſie,</hi> and
<hi>General.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is <hi>Rational;</hi> for not only the <hi>Foundation,</hi> but
the <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructures</hi> too, are ſquared out by <hi>natural
Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is <hi>Compendious:</hi> for, the whole ſubſtance of the
Method is comprehended in <hi>ſix ſhort points;</hi> which yet I draw into
a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower Circle.</p>
            <p>It is <hi>Clear:</hi> interwoven only <pb facs="tcp:29434:10"/>with plain, and
general notions, and deveſted from all <hi>Scholaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal queſtions;</hi>
which of purpoſe I have waved: For my perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion always has been, That
<hi>Pole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Debates,</hi> wherein we han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle matters of Religion, which
<hi>we cannot deny without for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting our Faith,</hi> are not to be involved
with <hi>Scholaſtical</hi> Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; which we may promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<hi>deny,</hi> or <hi>defend,</hi> without any prejudice to our Religion, For,
then the conteſt comes to be, not between <hi>Catholick,</hi> and
<hi>no-Catholick,</hi> but between <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> and
<hi>Catholiques:</hi> neither do I ſee what neceſſity there is, that men
ſhould be made <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, Scotiſts,</hi> or <hi>Suariſts,</hi>
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be made <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> or <hi>Catholiques:</hi> or why
Thoſe, who <pb facs="tcp:29434:11"/>
               <hi>come</hi> to our Religion, ſhould not have
<hi>the ſame liberty,</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to opinions, as Thoſe, who are of our
Religion.</p>
            <p>It is <hi>Eaſie:</hi> For; that one may underſtand this
Method, it is not neceſſary, that he be <hi>vers'd in Fathers,
Councils,</hi> or <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures,</hi> nor that he has <hi>read Books of
Controverſie,</hi> nor that he be a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> or a
<hi>Divine,</hi> nor that he be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the <hi>Latin, Greek,</hi> or
<hi>Hebrew</hi> Tongue; nay, nor that he be ſo much as <hi>able to read.</hi>
It is only neceſſary, that he be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and that
he be able to reflect <hi>upon his own Thoughts;</hi> which any rational man is
able to do. For my Task, in this Method, only is, among ſo many <hi>general
Notions,</hi> which <pb facs="tcp:29434:11"/>either <hi>Nature,</hi> or <hi>Education,</hi>
hath printed in the hearts of all men, <hi>to trace out ſuch,</hi> as being
<hi>rallied</hi> together, will certainly <hi>conveigh</hi> one to the <hi>True
Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi> So that my deſign is, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſhew <hi>every one,</hi>
how he may convince <hi>himſelf,</hi> than to convince him <hi>my
ſelf.</hi> And though few are willing to <hi>yield to others,</hi> in
conteſts of great concern; yet no Body is unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to <hi>yield to
himſelf,</hi> and his <hi>own Notions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, laying aſide all <hi>Animoſities,</hi> and
<hi>Feuds of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes,</hi> which many hate ſo much, we deal fairly, and
freely, with our Adverſary, making him <hi>his own Book,</hi> and only
pointing out unto him, by way of <hi>an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatory,</hi> ſuch Principles
as <pb facs="tcp:29434:12"/>are material to our intent.</p>
            <p>Finally, it is <hi>General;</hi> for the <hi>Satisfaction</hi> of
<hi>all perſons,</hi> for the <hi>confirmation</hi> of <hi>all Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi>
of Faith, and for the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation</hi> of <hi>all Errors</hi> againſt
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. It is <hi>General</hi> for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of <hi>all
perſons,</hi> whether they be <hi>learned,</hi> or <hi>unlearned,</hi>
whether they be <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> or no <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and whether
they be of <hi>any Religion,</hi> or of <hi>no Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi> Yea it is
<hi>General,</hi> as well for ſuch as ſeek <hi>their own Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction</hi>
in matters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as for ſuch as deſire to <hi>ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
others.</hi> Nor Thoſe, who will make uſe of This Method, have any need of
<hi>Books;</hi> much leſs of <hi>great Libraries:</hi> and whatever way our
Adverſary takes to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taque us, we may <hi>force</hi> him to <pb facs="tcp:29434:12"/>
               <hi>our Method.</hi> So that whoever is well acquainted therewith,
needs not any <hi>particular preparation</hi> to encounter any Adverſary, of
whatſoever Sect or profeſſion he be.</p>
            <p>It is alſo <hi>General,</hi> for the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation</hi> of
<hi>all Articles</hi> of Faith. For we ſhew at once the <hi>Truth</hi> of
<hi>All ſuch Articles:</hi> and not only of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch as <hi>are now</hi> Articles of Faith, but of ſuch
too, as ſhall <hi>hereafter be declared to be ſo.</hi> We inſinuate
alſo, how This Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod may be <hi>applied</hi> to any <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
point;</hi> wherein ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is deſired. Wherefore, when one is to
diſpute with another, of whatſoever Religion he be, if he will
<hi>adjuſt</hi> himſelf to <hi>This</hi> Method, there is no need to
<hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe him beforehand,</hi> of what <pb facs="tcp:29434:13"/>particular Point they
are to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, it is <hi>General</hi> for the <hi>Confutation</hi> of
<hi>all Errors</hi> in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: not only of ſuch as <hi>have been,</hi> or
<hi>are,</hi> but alſo of ſuch, as <hi>ſhall</hi> (perhaps) <hi>hereafter
be hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched.</hi> So that, though the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of theſe times ſhould
<hi>go out of faſhion,</hi> (as probably they will) and others come <hi>into
vogue,</hi> there will be no need of ſeeking a <hi>new Method,</hi> or
<hi>way</hi> to confute them.</p>
            <p>Many ſpend much time in ſeeking out the True Religion, yet
<hi>never find it:</hi> and the reaſon is, becauſe they do not take <hi>the
right way:</hi> yea they never enquire, whether the way they take <hi>be right,
or not.</hi> And let a Thing be never ſo eaſie to be met with, <pb facs="tcp:29434:13"/>yet if one takes the <hi>wrong way,</hi> he will <hi>never,</hi> or
<hi>ſcarce ever,</hi> meet with it.</p>
            <p>The firſt enquiry therefore muſt be about <hi>the way,</hi> to
find out the True Religion. Our Sectaries com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly run <hi>to Scriptures,</hi>
as <hi>the only way</hi> so find it out; and to that Scripture which
<hi>chance</hi> or <hi>Education</hi> has put into their hands, without ever
examining whether it be <hi>true,</hi> and <hi>entire Scripture,</hi> or no.
Others addreſs themſelves to the <hi>Doctors</hi> of the Religion
<hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, where they were born;
<hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing,</hi> rather then <hi>proving,</hi> ſuch a Religion to be
true; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reflecting, that men will be ſure to <hi>prefer</hi> the
Religion they profeſs, whether <hi>True,</hi> or <hi>Falſe,</hi> before all
others. And though I <pb facs="tcp:29434:14"/>cannot deny, but that ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have
gotten into the True Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion <hi>by chance,</hi> or upon <hi>frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
grounds;</hi> and that if they conform thereunto, <hi>they will be
ſaved:</hi> yet certainly whoever comes to know, that the
<hi>induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> he had to embrace the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion he is a member of, were
<hi>very ſlight,</hi> and <hi>inſignificant,</hi> he will, if he tenders
his own Salvation, endeavour to find out <hi>Solid Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives:</hi> which if he
cannot find in the Religion he hitherto has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, he is bound to
ſeek them elſewhere.</p>
            <p>I believe, that the Fate of this Diſcourſe will be the ſame,
as that of other ſuch Diſcourſes, which are grounded <hi>upon
Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> viz. that there will be ſome, who when they have nothing
elſe <pb facs="tcp:29434:14"/>to ſay, will cry out <hi>Sophiſtry, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry.</hi>
But we muſt not be ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with meer words. Let them legally ſhew,
wherein <hi>the Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,</hi> or <hi>Fallacy,</hi> of any of our Arguments
does conſiſt; or at leaſt that they are <hi>Sophiſtical,</hi> and
<hi>Fallacious:</hi> and they will do ſomething. But if they be not able to
do neither of theſe Things; <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws of rational
Diſcourſe,</hi> they must confeſs themſelves <hi>Non pluſt,</hi> and
if to ſay only, without any legal proof, That an <hi>Argument is
Sophiſtical,</hi> be enough to anſwer it, what Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is there. though
never <hi>ſo concluding,</hi> which may not eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be anſwered?</p>
            <p>And to put an end to this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, I entreat ſuch, as ſhall
take the pains to read this <hi>preſent me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod,</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:29434:15"/>that they
would be pleaſed to peruſe it with <hi>care,</hi> and <hi>dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</hi>
For, even the <hi>cleareſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations</hi> are not underſtood,
unleſs they be conſidered <hi>with at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,</hi> and that they would
ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend their judgment thereof, till <hi>they have read it all over,</hi>
we having ſet down after <hi>the ſix points,</hi> wherein the Method
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, ſeveral things, which contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute much, to clear the
<hi>difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> that may occur againſt it. And ſince there is no
Book ſo <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate,</hi> as that it has been appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>by all,</hi>
eſpecially if it treats of points controverted: nor none ſo
<hi>unfortunate,</hi> as that it has not been approved <hi>by ſome:</hi> Such
as ſhall <hi>approve</hi> of this Method, will at a very little expence have
reaped a <hi>conſiderable Fruit,</hi> viz. <pb facs="tcp:29434:15"/>a <hi>Compendious
way</hi> to ſatisfie <hi>themſelves,</hi> and <hi>others,</hi> in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
of Religion: and ſuch as ſhall <hi>not approve</hi> of it, will have no
juſt reaſon <hi>to complain</hi> of me, as if I had put them to any great
expence either of <hi>Time</hi> or <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29434:16"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29434:16"/>
            <head>A RATIONAL, Compendious way, TO Convince, without any
Diſpute, all Perſons whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Diſſenting from the TRUE
RELIGION.</head>
            <p>ALL perſons whatſoever, that Diſſent from the True
Religion, (which we ſhall prove to be the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique) muſt be either of no
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; or of a Falſe Religion, as is manifeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:29434:17"/>If they be of no Religion, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they deny a
True God, and conſequently a true Religion, as Atheiſts: or they grant a
True God, but deny a True Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as Deiſts.</p>
            <p>If they be of a Falſe Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, either they deny a Reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
Religion, but grant a natural Religion, as Libertines and Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinarians: or
they grant a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Religion, but deny Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, as Jews,
Turks, and Pagans: or they grant Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, but deny Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
Religion; as rigid Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants: or finally, they grant Catholick Religion to
be a true Religion, and free from all Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental errors: but withal they
affirm, that it teaches <hi>us Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Faith,</hi> ſeveral Errors, and 
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:29434:17"/>Corruptions; and conſequently, that it is not Free from
all Errors and Corruptions whatſoever; as moderate Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>And becauſe it is impoſſible to convince any one of his
er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, but out of Principles, or Poſitions, which he himſelf does grant,
as is evident: we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that there is no body, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he be
manifeſtly either a Mad man or a Fool, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence uncapable to be
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed with, who does not grant <hi>SOMETHING TO BE TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E.</hi> For,
if <hi>nothing be true,</hi> then it is not True, that he, with whom we
Diſpute, is in his wits; that he is rather a man, than a Block; that he
affirms, or denies, or doubts: Nay, it is not true, that <hi>Nothing is
True.</hi> For, if <pb n="4" facs="tcp:29434:18"/>this be true, then <hi>Something</hi> is
true.</p>
            <p>Upon this Suppoſition, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>there is
ſomething True,</hi> (which no rational man can que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion) I ground this
preſent Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, to convince all perſons whatſoever, diſſenting from
the true Religion. For, if there be <hi>ſomething True,</hi> we ſhall prove
that <hi>there is a true God;</hi> and if there be a true God, That <hi>there
is ſome true Religion;</hi> and if there be ſome True Religion, that there
is <hi>ſome true revealed Religion;</hi> and if there be ſome true revealed
Religion, that <hi>Chriſtian Religion is true;</hi> and if Chriſtian
Religion be true, <hi>that Catholique Religion;</hi> and by conſequence
<hi>Free from all Fundamental Errors,</hi> and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <pb n="5" facs="tcp:29434:18"/>if
Catholique Religion be true, and free from all Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental errors, that it
does not teach as <hi>an Article of Faith,</hi> any error, or corruption; and
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, that it is free from all errors, and corruptions
whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. For <hi>Catholique Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or <hi>Catholique Faith</hi>
is taken here, as it comprehends all Thoſe Doctrines, and <hi>only
Thoſe,</hi> which the Catholique Church Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, as <hi>Articles of Divine
Faith.</hi> And thus we ſhall convince all perſons whatſoever,
diſſenting from the true Religion and Faith, that is, <hi>from the
Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Religion and Faith.</hi> For all Diſſenters imaginable are
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in the forementioned Claſſes.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:29434:19"/>I. If there <hi>be ſomething True,</hi>
I prove that there is a <hi>True God.</hi> For, if there <hi>be ſome Thing
true,</hi> let's ſuppoſe that it is true, That <hi>there is ſomething
better than an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other;</hi> this being an evident Truth aſſented unto by all
rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal men: and whoever denies, that there is ſomething better than
another, muſt neceſſarily deny himſelf to be better than an aſs or a
block. For, if he be better, then there is ſomething better, than another.
And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, whoever comes to deny himſelf to be better than an Aſs, or
a Block, is either a mad-man, or a fool; and conſequently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to be
diſcourſed with any further. Now, if there be ſomething better than
another, <hi>there is ſomething the beſt of all <pb n="7" facs="tcp:29434:19"/>Things.</hi> For one thing is better then another, becauſe it comes
nearer that, which is the beſt of all things. And how can it come nearer
that, which is not? It is a common Maxim amongſt Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers,
<hi>Supremum in unoquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que genere eſt menſura reliquo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum in eodem
genere.</hi> The beſt, and greateſt in each kind is the meaſure of the
reſt in the ſame kind. For one thing is ſaid to be better than another in
ſuch a kind, becauſe it comes nearer that, which is the beſt. A Duke is
better in Dignity than an Earl, becauſe he comes nearer the King; who is the
beſt man of the Kingdom in Dignity. So that unleſs in each kind there be
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſomething, <hi>that is the beſt,</hi> there can be no rule, nor 
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29434:20"/>meaſure, whereby one Thing may be judged better than
ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſuch a kind. Wherefore if it be true, that there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
better than another, there muſt be <hi>ſomething the beſt of all
Things:</hi> and if ſo, then there is a True God. For the very no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a
true God is <hi>Ens Opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum Maximum,</hi> the Beſt and Greateſt of all
Things; as all, even Atheiſts do confeſs, as we ſuppoſe: for unleſs
we agree a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the notion of God, there can be no Diſpute between us. Yea,
what is the Beſt of all Things that exiſt, is alſo the beſt of all
Things that are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. For nothing poſſible can exiſt, or be
produced, but by virtue of ſomething, that does exiſt: and nothing can
produce <pb n="9" facs="tcp:29434:20"/>what is better than it ſelf, <hi>Nemo dat, quod
non habet.</hi> No body gives what he has not. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude therefore, that if
it be true (as certainly it is) that there is ſomething better than another,
there is a true God.</p>
            <p n="2">II. If there be a True God, I prove, that there is ſome
True Religion. For, if there be a True God, we ought to worſhip him, in what
manner he will be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped by us; and obey him, in what matters he will be
obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by us. Subjects ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, and obey their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, and
Servants their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, in what manner, and in what matters they require:
and if there be a true God, the Beſt and greateſt of all things, <hi>Ens 
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29434:21"/>optimum, Maximum,</hi> certainly he is <hi>King of Kings,
and Lord of Lords, and Supreme Governour of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe:</hi> and we are
his <hi>Subjects,</hi> and <hi>Servants;</hi> as no Body, who grants a True
God, can deny. We ought therefore to reſpect, and obey God. Yea, what is to
be reſpected, or who is to be obeyed, if God be not? the Beſt of All
things, the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Monarch? If we ought to worſhip God in what manner
he will be worſhipped by us, and obey him in what matters he will be obeyed
by us; there muſt be ſome Doctrine teaching us, in what manner God will be
worſhipped by us, and in what matters he will be obeyed by us. For how can we
worſhip or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey God, if we neither know <pb n="11" facs="tcp:29434:21"/>in what manner
we are to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him, nor in what matters we are to obey him? For, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
God will <hi>aſſign, by Himſelf,</hi> the particular manner of the
worſhip to be given to him, or will <hi>leave the aſſignation thereof to
men</hi> (and he muſt neceſſarily do either the one or the other) we
muſt obey his will; and to obey it, we muſt know it. And how can we know
it, unleſs there be ſome Doctrine, that teaches it? If there be ſome
Doctrine teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us in what manner God will be worſhiped by us, and in what
matters he will be obeyed by us, there muſt be ſome true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. For by
a true Religion we underſtand, according to the common notion thereof, <hi>a
Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that teaches men, in what <pb n="12" facs="tcp:29434:22"/>manner God will be
worſhip'd by them, and in what matters he will be obeyed by them.</hi>
Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I conclude, that if there be a True God (as has been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) there
is ſome True Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p n="3">III. If there be ſome True Religion, I prove, that there
is ſome true <hi>revealed</hi> Religion. For, if there be ſome true
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, there is ſome Doctrine teaching us, in what manner God will be
worſhip'd by us, and in what matters he will be obeyed by us; for this is the
notion of a true Religion, as we have ſeen. If there be ſome ſuch
Doctrine, <hi>it muſt be revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led unto us by God.</hi> For how can we know
<hi>Gods will,</hi> unleſs <pb n="13" facs="tcp:29434:22"/>he reveal it unto us, either
<hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately</hi> by himſelf, or <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately</hi> by others,
commiſſioned by him? <hi>Natural Religion,</hi> or the <hi>Light of
nature,</hi> teaches us only in general, That we are to worſhip God, in what
man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner he will be worſhip'd by us, and that we are to obey him in what
matters he will be obeyed by us: But it does not tell us (as is manifeſt) the
<hi>particular manner,</hi> wherewith he requires we would worſhip him, nor
the <hi>particular matters,</hi> wherein he requires we ſhould obey him:
which doubtleſs may be very different. And of what concern is it, that we
know we are to worſhip and obey God, if we neither know, <hi>how</hi> we are
to worſhip him, nor <hi>in what</hi> we <pb n="14" facs="tcp:29434:23"/>we are to obey
him? Yea, ſhould God be pleaſed to leave to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one the choice of the
man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, wherein he is to worſhip him; yet ſince this would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be a
<hi>very particular man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> of worſhip, not intimated unto us by the Law
of Nature, God <hi>muſt reveal it.</hi> God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt <hi>reveal</hi>
unto us, in what particular manner he will be worſhipped by us, and in what
particular matters he will be obeyed by us. And if ſo; then there is ſome
true <hi>revealed</hi> Religion; which is nothing elſe, but a
<hi>Doctrine</hi> teaching men in what particular manner God will be
worſhipped by them, and in what particular matters he will be obeyed by them,
<hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed by God.</hi> Wherefore I <pb n="15" facs="tcp:29434:23"/>conclude, that if
there be ſome <hi>True</hi> Religion, (as has been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that there is)
there is ſome <hi>true revealed</hi> Religion.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. If there be ſome true <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed</hi> Religion, I
prove, that <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion is true. For, if there be ſome
<hi>true Revealed</hi> Religion, certainly, That a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all Religions that
pretend to be revealed by God, muſt be true, which can evidently ſhew, that
it has been <hi>miraculouſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated.</hi> For a miraculous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation
cannot be effected <hi>without true, and real Miracles;</hi> and True and Real
Miracles are Gods <hi>Broad Seal,</hi> and <hi>manifeſt proofs</hi> of
<hi>the Truth;</hi> in whoſe Confirmation they are wrought, and a <hi>certain
kind of Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation;</hi> 
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:29434:24"/>Becauſe God can ſpeak
as well by <hi>works,</hi> as by <hi>words.</hi> All profeſſors of
revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Religions either pretend to produce true, and real Miracles in
confirmation of their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Religions, or at leaſt would be glad, if
they could produce them. Yea even Atheiſts openly profeſs, that could they
be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of a true, and real Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, done in Confirmation of a Truth,
they ſhould think themſelves bound to ſubmit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. Wherefore a true,
and real Miracle, according to the unanimous conſent of men, is a pregnant
proof of the Thing, in whoſe confirmation it is wrought. If that Religion,
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all that pretend to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed by God, <hi>be True,</hi> which 
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29434:24"/>can evidently ſhew that it has been <hi>miraculouſly
propagated,</hi> certainly, that muſt be true, which can evidently ſhew,
that though it contains ſeveral my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, far above the reach of Humane
Reaſon, and divers ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities, very contrary to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane inclination, yet
has been <hi>propagated</hi> over a great part of the world, <hi>without the
help of Arms,</hi> or <hi>humane Enticements,</hi> by men of themſelves very
unfit for ſo great a work; overcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing other Religions eſtabliſhed in the
world, which preached liberty and pleaſures. For the propagation of ſuch a
Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and in ſuch a manner, (to uſe St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi>'s
argument)<note place="margin">Lib. 22. De Civitat. Dei, cap. 5.</note> either 
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29434:25"/>was effected <hi>with Miracles,</hi> or <hi>without
them.</hi> If <hi>with them,</hi> then it was miraculouſly propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated: which
is what we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend. If <hi>without them;</hi> what greater Miracle than this,
<hi>viz.</hi> that ſuch a Religion ſhould be propagated in ſuch a manner,
and that without any Miracle! If ſuch a Religion propagated in the manner
aforeſaid, <hi>be true,</hi> then certainly <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> is
true. For it is evident, as even the enemies of Chriſtianity do confeſs,
that Chriſtian Religion has been propagated over a great part of the world,
that it contains ſeveral Myſteries, as the <hi>Trinity, Incarnation,
Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi> and others, far above the reach of humane reaſon; and
diverſe ſeverities, as to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace <pb n="19" facs="tcp:29434:25"/>croſſes, to love
our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to mortifie our paſſions, and others, very contrary to
hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane inclination; that it over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Paganiſm eſtabliſhed in the world,
which preached li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and pleaſures: and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that being ſuch, it
was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated <hi>without the help of Arms,</hi> or <hi>humane
Enticements,</hi> by the Apoſtles, and other A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical men, very unfit
of themſelves for ſo great a work. All this (I ſay) is granted even by
the enemies of Chriſtianity; and is manifeſt from <hi>Authentick
Hiſtory,</hi> and <hi>conſtant Tradition:</hi> and ſhould our
Adverſaries de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny any of the forementioned circumſtances, they may be
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved againſt them out of the <hi>ſame Topicks,</hi> and with the
<hi>ſame <pb n="20" facs="tcp:29434:26"/>Evidence,</hi> as other <hi>ancient
mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> of Fact; which to deny, or queſtion, even to them, would ſeem
a madneſs. Wherefore I conclude, that if there be ſome true
<hi>revealed</hi> Religion, (as has been proved) Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is
true.</p>
            <p n="5">V. If Chriſtian Religion be true, I prove, that
<hi>Catholique</hi> Religion is true. By <hi>Catholique Religion</hi> I
underſtand <hi>Roman Catholique,</hi> as will appear by my proofs: and there
is no other <hi>Catholique</hi> Religion, but the <hi>Roman.</hi> If
Chriſtian Religion be true, it may ſolidly be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved againſt the enemies
thereof; as we have proved it already, and as all profeſſors of
Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity do grant. Otherwiſe, why <pb n="21" facs="tcp:29434:26"/>ſhould they
preach it, if they cannot prove it? If Chriſtian Religion may be ſolidly
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; a <hi>Religion,</hi> that has the <hi>ſame proofs</hi> as
Chriſtianity has, or <hi>any of them,</hi> that are <hi>Solid;</hi> muſt
needs be true. For it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, that there ſhould be any ſolid,
or real proof of a Falſity, according to that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, <hi>Ex vero tantum
non ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur falſum.</hi> From Truth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone no Falſity can be deduced.
If a Religion that has the ſame proofs <hi>as Chriſtianity has,</hi> be
true, then <hi>Catholique Religion</hi> is true; for it has the <hi>ſame
proofs</hi> as Chriſtianity: which will manifeſtly appear, if one reflects
upon the grounds, whereby Chriſtians do commonly ſhew the truth of
Chriſtianity againſt <pb n="22" facs="tcp:29434:27"/>her enemies. And becauſe our
Adverſaries in this point, do profeſs themſelves to be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, we
ask them, why they are, or what ration<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al inducement they have to be
Chriſtians? or (which comes to the ſame) what ſolid proof can they
produce to ſhew the Truth of Chriſtianity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the enemies thereof?
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſing them, that it cannot be a ſolid proof of the Truth of
Chriſtianity, that which agrees to <hi>Judaiſm, Paganiſm,</hi> or
<hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometiſm,</hi> which we, <hi>as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> believe to be
falſe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions: And how can we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade our ſelves, that Chriſtian
Religion is true, if we have no better proofs for it, than are for a Religion,
which we firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <pb n="23" facs="tcp:29434:27"/>believe to be falſe? And let's
ſuppoſe, That our Adverſaries chuſe the reaſon above-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, of
<hi>the miraculous propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Chriſtianity;</hi> which is a common,
ſolid, and evident proof: the ſame would be, ſhould they produce any
other ſolid proof of Chriſtianity. For it may be eaſily applied to
<hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Religion.</hi> Now, if the truth of Chriſtian Religion be
ſolidly proved, becauſe it was propagated in the manner above inſinuated,
the Truth alſo of <hi>Catholique Religion</hi> is ſolidly proved by the
like propagation. For, the <hi>Roman Catholique</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion (as even our
Adverſaries do confeſs, who blame her up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that account) does contain,
beſides the general principles of <pb n="24" facs="tcp:29434:28"/>Chriſtianity
before-mentioned, very hard myſteries above the reach of humane reaſon; as
(for inſtance) <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> which thwarts (as they ſay)
all Senſe and Reaſon; and very hard Precepts, and Counſels, contrary to
humane inclination, as <hi>Vows, Faſts, Conſeſſion, Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition</hi>
for <hi>Prieſts</hi> to Marry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, the <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique</hi> Religion, even as
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining ſuch Doctrines as our Adverſaries ſtile errors, and
corruptions, has been propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted over a great part of the world, without
<hi>the help of Arms,</hi> or <hi>humane Enticements,</hi> by men, who were
commonly Strangers, and very unfit of themſelves, to reclaim, as they did,
ſo vaſt a multitude of people from <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſm,</hi> 
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:29434:28"/>eſtabliſhed among them, which preached Liberty and
Pleaſures, to Chriſtian and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Religion, which prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
Mortification, and Severi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. So St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> the Monk converted
<hi>England,</hi> and St. <hi>Xa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verius</hi> divers Nations among the Indians;
and ſeveral others have done the like in other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries; who were <hi>Roman
Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques,</hi> and preached the <hi>Roman Catholique</hi> Religion: All
which is granted by moſt of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries; and againſt ſuch, as
ſhall deny any of the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned circumſtances, they may be made as
manifeſt out of <hi>Authentique Hiſtory,</hi> and <hi>Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> as
we, or they, can make manifeſt againſt Pagans, the like circumſtances, in
the propagati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <pb n="26" facs="tcp:29434:29"/>of Chriſtian Religion: and whatever
exception they make againſt this proof, or others commonly alledged for
Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion, was, or might be made by the enemies of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,
againſt the like proofs alledged for Chriſtian Religion: (and certainly
there cannot be a ſolid exception made againſt a Truth:) and what they
would anſwer the enemies of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in that caſe, if they anſwer
ſolidly, we anſwer the ſame. Now (to uſe St. <hi>Auguſtins</hi>
Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument) the propagation of the <hi>Roman Catholique</hi> Religion in the
manner aforeſaid, either was done <hi>with Miracles,</hi> or <hi>without
them.</hi> If <hi>with them,</hi> then it was miraculouſly propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated, and
conſequently is true: <pb n="27" facs="tcp:29434:29"/>if <hi>without them,</hi> what
greater Miracle than this, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſuch a Religion ſhould be
propagated in ſuch a manner, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Miracle? Wherefore ſince
we have the ſame proofs, and grounds, for <hi>Catholique</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as
for <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> if we will proceed rationally, we muſt be both
<hi>Catholiques,</hi> and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians;</hi> or otherwiſe we can neither
be <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> nor <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques.</hi> And therefore I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,
that if <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be true, as has been proved,
<hi>Catholique</hi> Religion is true.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. If <hi>Catholique</hi> Religion be true, I prove, that
it teaches nothing whatſoever, <hi>as an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Faith,</hi> which is not
True, or which is an error, or <pb n="28" facs="tcp:29434:30"/>corruption. For, if
<hi>Catholique</hi> Religion be true, it is free from all <hi>Fundamental, and
Eſſential Errors,</hi> as is manifeſt: all ſuch Errors being
deſtructive to the very <hi>Being of a True Religion.</hi> If Catholique
Religion be Free from all <hi>Fundamental Errors,</hi> it does not err
againſt any <hi>Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental point</hi> of Religion. For a
<hi>Fundamental</hi> error in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is nothing elſe, but an error
againſt a <hi>Fundamental</hi> point of Religion. If Catholique Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
does not err againſt any <hi>Fundamental point</hi> of Religion, then it does
not err againſt this point, <hi>viz. That God is not the Author of any error,
or corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption whatſoever;</hi> this being, doubtleſs, <hi>a Fundamental
point</hi> of Religion; as all, who admit <pb n="29" facs="tcp:29434:30"/>any Religion, do
conſeſs. If Catholique Religion does not err againſt the fore-mentioned
point, it does not teach God to <hi>be the Author of any error, or corruption,
whatſoever,</hi> or of any thing whatſoever, which is either an error, or
corruption: for to teach this, is to err againſt the forementioned point; as
is evident. If Catholique Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on does not teach God to be the Author of any
error or corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption whatſoever, it does not teach any thing whatſoever as
<hi>an Article of Faith,</hi> which is either an error, or corruption. For to
teach a Thing as an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Faith, is to teach <hi>God to be the Author of
it,</hi> or that it has been delivered by God; as all do grant. Now ſince it
is <pb n="30" facs="tcp:29434:31"/>manifeſt, according to the una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous conſent of
both Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, and Proteſtants, (who blame us upon this account) that the
Roman Catholique Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion teaches, as <hi>Articles of Faith,</hi> Purgatory,
Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, Invocation of Saints, Veneration of Images, Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of Chriſt in the Euchariſt, Infallibility of the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church,
its perpetui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the end of the world, our Canon of Scripture, and other
Doctrinal Points controverted between us, and them; it muſt needs follow,
that none of theſe Points are either errors or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions. In the like
manner we may conclude the ſame of any particular Point, which comes under
debate: as (for inſtance) <pb n="31" facs="tcp:29434:31"/>I prove
<hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> to be no error, nor corruption. The Roman
Catholique Religion does not teach any thing as an <hi>Article of Faith,</hi>
which is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an error, or a corruption; as has been ſhewn; otherwiſe it
would not be a <hi>True Religion.</hi> But the <hi>Roman Catholique</hi>
Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion does teach, as an <hi>Article of Faith, Tranſubſtantiation,</hi>
as all do confeſs. Therefore <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation</hi> is no error,
nor corruption. Wherefore I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That if Catholique Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be true (as
has been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) it teaches nothing as <hi>an Article of Faith,</hi> (neither
does it, as here it is taken, teach any thing, but what it teaches <hi>as
ſuch</hi>) which is either an <hi>error,</hi> or a <hi>corruption:</hi> and
conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently <pb n="32" facs="tcp:29434:32"/>it is free from <hi>all errors, and
corruptions</hi> whatſoever: which is what we pretended to prove.</p>
            <p>And to draw into a cloſer Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle all the forementioned proofs,
ſuppoſing that it is true, That <hi>there is ſomething better than
another,</hi> the proof of a true Deity runs thus. If <hi>there be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
better than another,</hi> there is <hi>ſomething the beſt of All
Things.</hi> If there be <hi>ſomething the Beſt of All Things,</hi> there
is a <hi>True God.</hi> Therefore if there <hi>be ſomething better than
another,</hi> as certainly there is, <hi>there is a true God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>True Deity</hi> ſuppoſed, the proof of a <hi>True
Religion</hi> is fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in this manner. If we <hi>ought to Worſhip God</hi>
in what manner he will be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped <pb n="33" facs="tcp:29434:32"/>by us, and <hi>obey
him</hi> in what matters he will be obeyed by us, there muſt be <hi>ſome
Doctrine,</hi> teaching us, in what manner God will be worſhipped by us, and
in what matters he will be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by us. If there be <hi>ſome ſuch
Doctrine,</hi> then there is <hi>ſome true Religion.</hi> Therefore if we
ought to worſhip God, in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner he will be worſhipped by us, and to
obey him, in what matters he will be obeyed by us, (as, a True Deity
ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, doubtleſs we ought) there is <hi>ſome True
Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſing that there is <hi>ſome True Religion,</hi> the proof
of ſome true <hi>revealed</hi> Religion, is as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows. If there be ſome
<hi>Doctrine teaching us,</hi> in what manner God will be worſhipped by us, 
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29434:33"/>and in what matters he will be obeyed by us, it muſt
<hi>be reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God:</hi> if there be ſome <hi>ſuch Doctrine
revealed</hi> by God, there is ſome true <hi>revealed</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.
Therefore, if there be ſome <hi>Doctrine teaching us,</hi> in what manner God
will be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped by us, and in what mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters he will be obeyed by us, (as
evidently there is, a <hi>True Religion</hi> being ſuppoſed) there is
ſome true <hi>revealed</hi> Religion.</p>
            <p>Suppoſing that there is ſome <hi>true revealed Religion,</hi>
the proof of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion goes thus. If among all Religions
which pretend to be <hi>revealed</hi> by God, that muſt be true, which has
been <hi>miraculouſly propagated;</hi> certainly, that muſt be true; which,
though containing ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <pb n="35" facs="tcp:29434:33"/>Myſteries, far <hi>above the
reach of Humane Reaſon,</hi> and divers ſeverities <hi>very contrary</hi>
to <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Inclination,</hi> yet has been propagated over a great part of
the world, <hi>without the help of Arms,</hi> or <hi>humane Enticements,</hi>
by men very <hi>unfit</hi> of <hi>themſelves</hi> for ſo great a work; and
has overcome other <hi>Religions eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed</hi> in the world, which
<hi>preached liberty and pleaſures:</hi> If ſuch a Religion, propagated in
ſuch a manner, be true, then Chriſtian Religion is true. Therefore, if
among all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, which pretend to be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed</hi> by God, that
muſt be true, which has been <hi>miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly propagated;</hi> (as
cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it muſt, ſuppoſing that there is ſome true revealed
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion) <pb n="36" facs="tcp:29434:34"/>
               <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion is true.</p>
            <p>Suppoſing that <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is true, and that
the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned reaſon is ſolid, as doubtleſs it is; the proof of
<hi>Catholique</hi> Religion is thus. If Chriſtian Religion be true,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>propagated in the manner aforeſaid,</hi> a Religion, that
though containing as <hi>high My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries,</hi> and as <hi>hard Precepts</hi>
as Chriſtianity, yet has been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated in <hi>the like manner,</hi> muſt
needs be true. If ſo, then Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Religion is True. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if
Chriſtian Religion be true, becauſe propagated in the manner aforeſaid
(as beyond Debate it is in the foremention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuppoſition) Catholique
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is True.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:29434:34"/>Finally, ſuppoſing Catholick Religion to
be true, we prov'd, That it does not teach any thing as <hi>an Article of
Faith,</hi> which is not true, in this manner. If Catholique Religion be true,
it does not err againſt any <hi>Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Point;</hi> if ſo, it does not
teach any Thing as an <hi>Article of Faith,</hi> which is not true. Therefore,
if Catholique Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be true, as it is in the preſent ſuppoſition, it
does not teach any thing as <hi>an Article of Faith,</hi> which is not true; or
which is an error or corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>All theſe particular Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have been expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded more
at large in the former ſix Points.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:29434:35"/>But becauſe many of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries do
admit ſeveral of the forementioned points; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not
neceſſary to prove what our Adverſary of his own accord does admit, you
may begin with the ſixth, and laſt point, and ask your Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
whether he grants the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick Religion to be a true Religion? If he
grants it, then prove, according to the manner there ſet down, that it
teaches nothing as an Article of Faith, which is not true; or which is an
error, or corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If he denies it, then ask him, whether he grants
Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion to be true; If he grants it, then prove, in confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity
to the way contained in the fifth Point, that Catholick <pb n="39" facs="tcp:29434:35"/>Religion is true. If he denies it, then ask him, whether he grants any
revealed Religion to be true? If he grants it, then ſhew, according to the
Argument fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the fourth Point, that Chriſtian Religion is true. If he
denies it, then ask him, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he grants any true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? If he grants
it, then prove, according to the Diſcourſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the third Point, that
there is ſome true revealed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. If he denies it, then ask him, whether
he grants a True God? If he grants it, then prove, according to the Argument
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the ſecond Point, that there is ſome true Religion. If he
denies it, then ask him in the laſt place, whether he grants that there is
ſomething true? as <pb n="40" facs="tcp:29434:36"/>(for example) that there is
ſomething better than another? which he muſt grant, unleſs he be a Mad
man, or a Fool; and conſequently uncapable to be dealt with by
Diſcourſes: and then prove, according to the Argument couched in the
firſt Point, that there is a true God: proceeding always forwards, till you
have ſhewn, that the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ligion is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from all errors and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions
whatſoever: which is the drift of this ſhort Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>And ſince no Body does, or can diſſent from the Catholick
Religion, but upon the account of ſome Doctrine taught by it as <hi>an
Article of Faith,</hi> which the Diſſenter judges to be an error, or
corruption; what <pb n="41" facs="tcp:29434:36"/>more can be required to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the
judgment of all Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters whatſoever from the True and Catholick
Religion, than to prove (as we have done, in the fore-mentioned points) that it
does not teach any Thing whatſoever, as an <hi>Article of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Faith,</hi>
which is either an error, or corruption.</p>
            <p>From the fore-mentioned Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod we may infer by ſeveral
conſequences, (ſince one error produces another) that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever denies the
Catholick Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to be free from all errors, and corruptions whatſoever,
muſt needs deny himſelf to be better then a Mad man, or a Fool. For, if
Catholick Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion be not free from all errors <pb n="42" facs="tcp:29434:37"/>and
corruptions whatſoever, it muſt teach ſomething as <hi>an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of
Faith,</hi> which is either an error, or corruption. If it does teach
ſomething <hi>as an Article of Faith,</hi> which is either an error, or
corruption, it is not Free from <hi>all Fundamental Errors:</hi> if it be not
Free from all Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Errors, it is not <hi>True:</hi> if it be not true,
<hi>Chriſtian</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is <hi>not True:</hi> if Chriſtian Religion be
not True, no <hi>revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> Religion is True: if no <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed</hi>
Religion be true, <hi>no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is True:</hi> if no Religion be True, there
is <hi>no True God:</hi> if there be no True God, there is nothing <hi>the
Beſt of All Things:</hi> if there be nothing the Beſt of all Things, there
is nothing <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than another:</hi> and finally, if <pb n="43" facs="tcp:29434:37"/>there be <hi>nothing better than an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other,</hi> the perſon, with
whom we diſpute, is <hi>no better</hi> than a Mad man, or a Fool. So that,
whoever denies the Catholick Religion to be free from all er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and
corruptions whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, will be forced, unleſs he recants, to deny
himſelf to be better than a Mad man, or a Fool: which before any rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal
man will be forced to do, certainly, he will recal the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, from which
ſuch vaſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities are deduced; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly confeſs, that the
Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Religion, or Faith, is free from all errors, and corruptions
imaginable. And though the laſt Propoſition be deduced from ſeveral
precedent conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences; yet this Method is <pb n="44" facs="tcp:29434:38"/>common even
among Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticians, who are thought by all to proceed a moſt conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
and demonſtrative way.</p>
            <p>Moreover, according to the ſame Method, we may ſhew the Truth
of any Point, delivered by the Roman Catholique Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, <hi>as an Article of
Faith,</hi> whether it be ſpeculative or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical; of little, or great
mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hard and above the reach of Natural Reaſon; or eaſie and
ſuitable to Humane underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. For the Catholick Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (as we have
proved) does teach nothing <hi>as an Article of Faith,</hi> which is not true:
and ſure, it is againſt the very eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a true Religion, (ſuch
as the Catholick Religion is) to father upon God any thing that 
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:29434:38"/>that is not true, ſpeculative or practical, little or
great, hard or eaſie; and to teach a Thing as <hi>an Article</hi> of Faith,
is to father it upon God. And though Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks be commanded many Things by
their Eccleſiaſtical Superiours, (as Faſting upon Fridays, annual
Confeſſion, and ſuch like) which are no Articles of Faith; yet 'tis an
Article of Catholique Faith, that we are bound to obey our lawful Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours,
whether Eccleſiaſtical or Civil.</p>
            <p>And as concerning the <hi>hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of ſome Myſteries,
taught by the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion as <hi>Articles of Faith,</hi>
it can be no Argument to prove that it is not a true Religion. For, certain it
is, that God does <hi>know</hi> very high, and hard Myſteries, 
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:29434:39"/>far above the reach of humane underſtanding, and contrary
to the notions of Things here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. If he does <hi>know</hi> them, he may
<hi>reveal</hi> them. If he may <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal</hi> them, then a <hi>true
Religion</hi> (ſince it muſt be <hi>revealed</hi> by God) may
<hi>contain</hi> ſuch myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. And if a True Religion may
<hi>contain</hi> ſuch Myſteries, it can be no good argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that a
Religion is <hi>not true,</hi> becauſe it <hi>does contain</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry high,
and hard Myſteries, above the reach of humane un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and contrary
to the notions of Things, which hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane reaſon comprehends. Yea, the harder
the Myſteries are, which the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion does contain,
the <hi>more miraculous</hi> is the propagation thereof. For eaſie Things are
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:29434:39"/>believed with eaſe; but hard Things are not believed
with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great difficulty: And the more miraculous the propagati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the
<hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is, <hi>the more reaſon</hi> there is to
believe, that it is a true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>In the like manner, following the ſame Method, we may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince,
that the <hi>Roman</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion is, not only a <hi>True
Religion,</hi> but the <hi>true Religion;</hi> and that the <hi>Roman</hi>
Catholick Church is, not only a <hi>True Church,</hi> but the true Church: (By
a <hi>true Church</hi> we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand a Congregation of men that profeſs a
true Religion; and by the <hi>true Church</hi> we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the
Congregation of all ſuch, as profeſs the <hi>true <pb n="48" facs="tcp:29434:40"/>Religion;</hi> and a true Church and a true Religion are taken, as
con-diſtinguiſhed from a falſe Church, and a falſe Religion:) That out
of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church there is no Salvation, and that no Church, which
is not a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, is a Member of the True Church:
For all theſe Points are delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as <hi>Articles of Faith</hi> by the
<hi>Roman</hi> Church; as both we, and our Adverſaries do confeſs. That it
is, not only a <hi>True</hi> Religion, but alſo a <hi>ſound</hi> Religion.
For, what more can be required for <hi>the ſoundneſs</hi> thereof, than
that it ſhould not teach <hi>any corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whatſoever?</hi> as we have
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it does not. That it is <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely</hi> a true Religion, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
all Things neceſſary to be <pb n="49" facs="tcp:29434:40"/>believed, and all Things
neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be done, in order to Salvation; either <hi>neceſſitate
medii,</hi> or <hi>neceſſitate praecepti.</hi> For this alſo it delivers
as an <hi>Article of Faith.</hi> Yea, half a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is not a true Religion;
as half a man, <hi>viz.</hi> the Body a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone of a man, is not a true man. That
it is, not only <hi>True,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the <hi>Roman</hi> Church
deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers as <hi>an Article of Faith,</hi> and <hi>as revealed</hi> by God, but
alſo 'tis true, <hi>That it is an Article of Faith,</hi> and
<hi>revealed</hi> by God: as for example, not only the Myſtery of the Trinity
is <hi>true;</hi> but alſo 'tis true, that it is <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed.</hi> For it
is an <hi>Article of Faith, that thoſe Books,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Myſtery of
the Trinity is contained, and declared to <pb n="50" facs="tcp:29434:41"/>be ſo, are the
<hi>True Word,</hi> and <hi>Revelation of God.</hi> So that one would be an
Heretick, not only if he ſhould deny the Myſtery of the Trinity, but alſo
if he ſhould deny it to be <hi>revealed:</hi> and as one cannot be a true,
and loyal Subject, who counterfeits the Kings <hi>Hand</hi> and <hi>Seal;</hi>
ſo that Religion cannot be true, which <hi>Counterfeits Gods Word,</hi>
delivering (in order to <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize</hi> any Thing whatſoever) Things as
<hi>revealed</hi> by him, which he never revealed. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, that whatſoever
the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick Religion, or Church, teaches as <hi>an Article of
Faith,</hi> is not only true, but <hi>infallibly true.</hi> For, among other
Points, that it deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers as <hi>Articles of Faith,</hi> (and 
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:29434:41"/>conſequently are true) one is <hi>its own Infallibility
in matters of Faith;</hi> as all do grant. It is therefore true, that the
<hi>Roman</hi> Religion is <hi>Infallible</hi> in ſuch matters: and if ſo,
then it muſt neceſſarily follow, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it declares as <hi>a
matter of Faith,</hi> is infallibly true. For, it is impoſſible, that the
Sentence of an Infallible Judge ſhould be falſe.</p>
            <p>Beſides, ſince we have ſhewn that the <hi>Roman</hi>
Catholick Church is free from all <hi>Fundamental</hi> errors, it is
inferred,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it does not err a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any <hi>Fundamental Point
whatſoever,</hi> either mediately, or <hi>immediately.</hi> For, an error
does not ceaſe to be <hi>Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal,</hi> 
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:29434:42"/>becauſe it
is only mediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and by conſequence, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to a <hi>Fundamental</hi>
Point. For to be <hi>mediately</hi> oppoſite to a point, is to be oppoſite
to that point, and another point alſo, whereon the Truth of the former
depends. A Diſeaſe, or Wound does not ceaſe to be <hi>mortal,</hi>
becauſe it infers only <hi>mediately</hi> the death of a man, deſtroying
<hi>immediately</hi> only the Diſpoſitions neceſſary for the
conſervation of his life; which being once deſtroyed, there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows the
ſeparation between the Body and the Soul; wherein the Death of man formally
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it cannot be ſaid, That the <hi>Roman</hi>
Catholick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion does not err againſt any <pb n="53" facs="tcp:29434:42"/>
               <hi>Fundamental</hi> point, <hi>preciſely</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>it
holds all the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal points</hi> of the True Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For a Religion
may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict it ſelf, and err againſt that very point, which it holds.
Certainly, a Religion, which ſhould deny Chriſt to be God, would err
<hi>Fundamentally;</hi> and conſequently, would be no <hi>true Religion;</hi>
though it ſhould, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting it ſelf, hold at the ſame time; that
Chriſt is God, and all other poſitive points of the True Religion. To the
truth therefore of a Religion it is requiſite, not only that it
<hi>holds</hi> all Fundamental points of the true Religion; but alſo, that it
does <hi>not deny</hi> any of them, neither <hi>mediately,</hi> nor
<hi>immediately;</hi> obſerving, what <pb n="54" facs="tcp:29434:43"/>is related of St.
<hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> [Joan. 1.30] <hi>Confeſſus eſt, &amp; non
negavit:</hi> He confeſt, and did not deny.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That it cannot be affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That a Religion is true, and
conſequently, that it does not err againſt any <hi>Fundamental</hi> point,
becauſe <hi>ſome,</hi> who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs it, are excuſed by <hi>Invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Ignorance.</hi> For, invincible ignorance, though it excuſes him, who has it,
from <hi>erring maliciouſly,</hi> yet it does not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him <hi>from
erring;</hi> nor the Religion, which ſhould contain ſuch an error, from
being <hi>erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous,</hi> and <hi>heretical</hi> too, if the point, againſt
which it errs, be <hi>an Article of Faith.</hi> Sure, a man that ſhould ſay
<hi>That Chriſt is not God,</hi> would err <hi>Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally,</hi> 
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:29434:43"/>whether he ſaid it out of <hi>ignorance,</hi> or
<hi>malice:</hi> and a Religion, that ſhould teach ſuch an error, would be
an <hi>Heretical</hi> Religion, and err againſt a <hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental</hi>
point, <hi>viz.</hi> the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That a Religion, which teaches God to be the Author of
any Thing, that is <hi>really an error,</hi> muſt needs err againſt a
<hi>Fundamental</hi> point, though it teaches ſuch a Thing <hi>as a
Truth.</hi> For, to err, is to teach a Thing <hi>as a Truth,</hi> which
<hi>really</hi> is an <hi>error.</hi> The <hi>Arrians,</hi> doubtleſs, erred
againſt a <hi>Fundamental</hi> point, by teaching <hi>that Chriſt was not
God;</hi> which was really <hi>an error,</hi> though they thought it to be
<hi>a Truth.</hi> Wherefore the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Religion can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not 
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:29434:44"/>be free from all <hi>Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi> errors, unleſs
whatſoever it teaches <hi>as an Article of Faith</hi> be really true; and not
only <hi>judged</hi> by the Church to be ſo.</p>
            <p>According to the ſame Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod we convince at once the Truth of
all our Articles of Faith. For we have ſhewed, that whatſoever the
<hi>Roman</hi> Church teaches <hi>as an Article of Faith,</hi> is true;
otherwiſe, it would not be a <hi>true</hi> Church; and that there is <hi>no
Article of Faith,</hi> which is not delivered <hi>as ſuch</hi> by the
<hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church; otherwiſe it would not be <hi>entirely</hi> true.
Whence we avoid the tedious way of Treating Controverſies, (for which the
whole life of man is ſcarce ſufficient) <hi>viz.</hi> of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving each
point of Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie <pb n="57" facs="tcp:29434:44"/>by it ſelf, and out of its own
proper reaſons: though I do not hinder, but that we may prove ſome
particular points this way alſo; yet we have inſinuated above in the
ſixth Point, how we may apply this general way, to decide any particular
queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concerning matters of Faith; wherein the party, with whom we deal,
deſires ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>Again, the ſame Method will teach us, how we may, with eaſe,
diſcover all Hereſies whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. For it is eaſie to know, what
Doctrines are delivered by the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Church, (which we have
proved to be, not only a <hi>true,</hi> but the <hi>true</hi> Church) as
<hi>Articles of Faith;</hi> either out of the Canons of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councils,
admitted by <pb n="58" facs="tcp:29434:45"/>that Church, or out of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick
Catechiſms, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of Faith, uſed among Catholicks; or finally
out of the unanimous conſent of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Doctors: and if there be a Debate
among Catholick Writers, whether ſuch a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine be delivered by the
<hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Catholick Church as <hi>an Article of Faith;</hi> we oblige no
Body to look upon it as <hi>an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Faith</hi> of that Church: nay, the
conteſt between Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks and no Catholicks is not, whether ſuch
Doctrines be <hi>Articles of the Catholick Faith,</hi> or not, but whether they
be <hi>errors</hi> or <hi>truths.</hi> Now, if one knows, what Doctrines are
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by the Catholick Church, as <hi>Articles of Faith,</hi> 
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:29434:45"/>he may eaſily know, what Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions are
<hi>immediately</hi> oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to ſuch Doctrines. As for example, if one
knows, that <hi>Purgatory</hi> is delivered as an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Faith</hi> by
the Catholick Church, he cannot but ſee, that <hi>No-Purgatory,</hi> (or the
denial of <hi>Purgatory</hi>) is immediately op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to ſuch an Article.
And if one knows, what Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are <hi>immediately oppoſite</hi> to
ſuch Doctrines, as the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church delivers as <hi>Articles of
Faith,</hi> he knows alſo, what Propoſitions are <hi>Formal
Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies.</hi> For all <hi>Formal Here ſies</hi> whatſoever are
<hi>immediately</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to <hi>ſome Doctrine,</hi> taught by the
True Church (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Catholick) as an <hi>Article of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:29434:46"/>Moreover, if one knows; what other
Propoſitions do <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily infer</hi> any Formal He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, he
knows alſo, what Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions are <hi>virtual Hereſies.</hi> For a'l
<hi>virtual Hereſie</hi> muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily infer a <hi>Formal
Hereſie.</hi> And becauſe the <hi>Roman</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church is, not only
<hi>now</hi> the True Church, but will be till <hi>the worlds end;</hi> (for
among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, which ſhe delivers as <hi>Articles of Faith,</hi> one is
her own <hi>perpetuity</hi>) by help of this Method we are taught, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
what Hereſies now are, or have been; but alſo what Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies <hi>ſhall
be hereafter:</hi> if it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, that any <hi>new Hereſies</hi> be
broached. For all Hereſies what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever muſt, neceſſarily be
<hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> to <hi>ſome Doctrine</hi> delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <pb n="61" facs="tcp:29434:46"/>by the Catholick Church, as an <hi>Article of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet further, by the means of this Method we may ſolve all
<hi>Objections</hi> againſt the Truth of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Church,
or any Doctrine delivered by it as <hi>an Article of Faith;</hi> ſhewing in
general, That whatſoever is, or can be objected againſt us in this kind,
either from <hi>Reaſon,</hi> or <hi>Authority,</hi> is falſe, or
Incouclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive. For, if the <hi>Roman</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church be a
<hi>True</hi> Church, and if whatſoever ſhe teaches as <hi>an Article of
Faith,</hi> be <hi>True,</hi> as we have evinced; it follows evidently, that
what ever is, or can be, objected againſt our Church, or any Article thereof,
muſt neceſſarily be either <hi>Falſe,</hi> or <hi>Inconcluſive.</hi>
For it is a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt <pb n="62" facs="tcp:29434:47"/>principle of Logick, That <hi>there
can be no True, Solid, and Real Proof againſt a Truth, or of a
Falſity.</hi> True it is, that this Method doth not inſtruct us, how we are
to anſwer in <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular</hi> every. Objection againſt the Truth of the
<hi>Roman</hi> Church, and of the Doctrines which ſhe delivers as
<hi>Articles of Faith.</hi> But this is not neceſſary, to the end we may
remain <hi>fully ſatisfied,</hi> concerning the <hi>Falſity</hi> or
<hi>Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſiveneſs</hi> of whatſoever is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt her, or
her Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. All men are firmly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that there is <hi>Local
Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and that we move from one place to another, as <hi>reaſon,</hi>
and <hi>experience,</hi> do evidently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate; and conſequently,
according to the Principle juſt <pb n="63" facs="tcp:29434:47"/>now inſinuated, they
are <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vain,</hi> that whatſoever is object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt <hi>Local
Motion,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it ſeem never ſo hard, is either <hi>Falſe,</hi>
or <hi>Incluſive.</hi> Yet very few can ſhew <hi>directly,</hi> even with
<hi>probability,</hi> and perhaps no Body <hi>with evidence,</hi> how and why
each Objection in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar againſt <hi>Local Motion,</hi> is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>Falſe,</hi> or <hi>Inconcluſive.</hi> And generally ſpeaking, one may
be certain (as ſeveral obvious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances do evince) that ſuch a Thing is
ſo, without knowing, or being able to aſſign, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>particular
manner,</hi> how it is ſo; or the <hi>direct and proper reaſon,</hi> why it
is ſo: and conſequently one may be fully ſatisfied, that ſuch an
objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is either <hi>Falſe,</hi> or <hi>Inconclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive,</hi> 
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:29434:48"/>though he be not able to give the proper, and direct
rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why it is ſo.</p>
            <p>And although I muſt needs confeſs, that there are ſeveral
other ways, to demonſtrate the Truth of the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi>
Religion; as there may be <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſons,</hi> and all of them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good,
to prove the <hi>ſame Truth:</hi> yet it is eaſie to force our Adverſary
to come to this Method. For, all Methods what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, to prove the true
Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or any other verity, are grounded, either upon <hi>Reaſon,</hi> or
<hi>Authority.</hi> If our Adverſary will be tried by <hi>Reaſon,</hi> the
way we have taken in this Method, in order to find out the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, is
built upon <hi>Reaſon.</hi> For <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſhews us, that there is 
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:29434:48"/>
               <hi>ſomething better than another;</hi> and that if
<hi>there be ſomething better than another,</hi> there <hi>is a God,</hi> and
that if there <hi>be a God,</hi> there is a <hi>True Religion:</hi> and thus
<hi>Reaſon</hi> guides us down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, through the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Points, till
it has proved, That <hi>the Roman Catholick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion delivers nothing as an
Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Faith, which is not true:</hi> and that then we are to believe her
in whatſoever ſhe teaches <hi>as ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if our Adverſary will be tried by <hi>Authority,</hi> either
of <hi>Scriptures,</hi> or <hi>General Councils,</hi> or <hi>ancient
Fathers,</hi> or <hi>Modern Writers,</hi> This Trial, if it be well managed,
muſt depend upon the knowledge of the <hi>True Church,</hi> and <hi>True
Religion.</hi> For certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <pb n="66" facs="tcp:29434:49"/>no Body, in matters of
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, is bound to be tried by the Scriptures, Councils, or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of a
<hi>Falſe Religion.</hi> We cannot in prudence require of a Chriſtian to
ſtand, in Debates of Religion, to the Deciſions of the <hi>Alchoran,</hi>
the Scripture of the <hi>Turks;</hi> or to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of their Councils, and
Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors. Wherefore, when men appeal to <hi>Scriptures, Councils,</hi> or
<hi>Doctors,</hi> for the determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Religious Debates, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,
their intention is to appeal to ſuch Scriptures, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils (and
<hi>ſuch alone,</hi> and <hi>to all ſuch</hi>) as are admitted by the
<hi>True Church;</hi> and to ſuch Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors only, as are Members of <hi>the
True Religion.</hi> And how can we know, what Scriptures, or 
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:29434:49"/>what Councils, are <hi>admitted</hi> by the True Church; or
what Doctors are <hi>Members</hi> of the True Religion; unleſs we know, which
is <hi>the True Church,</hi> and which is <hi>the True Religion?</hi> For what
Saint <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaid of the Church in order to the Scripture,
<hi>Ego vero Evangelio non crederem, niſi me Eccleſiae Catholicae
commoveret authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas;</hi> [Aug. lib. Epiſt. cont. Manich. cap. 5.] may be
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to Councils, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors. For the <hi>preſent True</hi> Church
decides, not only what ancient Councils, and Doctors have been Orthodox, but
alſo what modern Councils, and Doctors are ſo. We force therefore our
Adverſary to the inveſtigation of the True Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; <pb n="68" facs="tcp:29434:50"/>and then we may ſet upon him, according to the Method
above-mentioned.</p>
            <p>Moreover, when one appeals to <hi>Scriptures, Councils,</hi> or
<hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> ſure he appeals to them as <hi>rightly underſtood.</hi>
For who will be tried by Scriptures, Councils, or Fathers, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in
<hi>a wrong ſenſe?</hi> Now if there ariſe a conteſt, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
there does, between us and our Adverſaries, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the right
meaning</hi> of the places, alledged out of <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> (the ſame is
of places alledged out of <hi>Councils,</hi> or <hi>Fathers</hi>) certainly the
<hi>Judge</hi> to decide this Debate, muſt appertain to the <hi>True
Religion.</hi> For, who will make his appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> to
decide <pb n="69" facs="tcp:29434:50"/>matters of Religion? or what <hi>Chriſtian</hi>
will go to a <hi>Turk,</hi> or a <hi>Jew,</hi> to determine mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters belonging
to Chriſtianity?</p>
            <p>In like manner, when one appeals to <hi>the private Spirit</hi> in
matters of Religion, ſure he will not appeal to the <hi>private Spirit</hi>
of an <hi>Atheiſt;</hi> or, if he be a Chriſtian, to the <hi>private
Spirit</hi> of a <hi>Jew,</hi> a <hi>Turk,</hi> or an <hi>Heretick.</hi> His
intention there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is to appeal to the <hi>private Spirit</hi> of ſuch as
are of the <hi>True Religion:</hi> and we cannot be aſcertain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, who, or what ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertains to the True
Religion, unleſs we be informed <hi>which the True Religion is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus we force our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary again, to make enquiry into
<hi>the True Religion;</hi> and <pb n="70" facs="tcp:29434:51"/>then we may attack him
after our own way: asking him, whether he grants the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick
Religion to be <hi>a true</hi> Religion? if he grants it, we may ſhew,
according to what we hinted above, That the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Religion
is <hi>the true</hi> Religion; and if ſo, that to her appertains the
judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Controverſie, and of the true, and genuine ſenſe of
<hi>Scriptures, Councils,</hi> and <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> Whence I conclude, that
till we have found out, <hi>which is the true Religion,</hi> ſcarce any other
Thing under Debate, appertaining to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, can be proved. And when that is
found out, all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Things appertaining to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion are proved without
dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:29434:51"/>And here I cannot but reflect upon the
unreaſonableneſs of our Adverſaries, who will tie us to <hi>certain</hi>
Topicks, without giving us leave to make uſe of <hi>others,</hi> of no leſs
force. Some will have us ſhew them in the <hi>Firſt Four General
Councils,</hi> or in the <hi>Fathers of the Firſt</hi> 600 <hi>years</hi>
after Chriſt, in <hi>expreſs</hi> terms, <hi>all the Points,</hi> which we
defend in oppoſition to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Church; and unleſs we can do it,
they proclaim the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory againſt us. And why might not we, in the ſame
man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, require of them to ſhew us in the Apoſtles Creed all their
<hi>Thirty Nine</hi> Articles? or in the Firſt Chapter of St.
<hi>Matthew's</hi> Goſpel, all the Myſteries of Chriſtian Religion? we
admit, <pb n="72" facs="tcp:29434:52"/>beſide the <hi>Four Firſt</hi> General Councils,
ſeveral others of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Authority: and beſide, the Fathers of the
<hi>Firſt</hi> 600 <hi>years,</hi> other Fathers, and Doctors.</p>
            <p>Others will have All Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies decided by <hi>expreſs
Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> and by <hi>their Scriptures</hi> only, and with their
<hi>verſions,</hi> and interpreted according to <hi>their ſenſe,</hi>
without hearkening either to <hi>Councils,</hi> or <hi>Fathers,</hi> or any
<hi>other Topicks,</hi> though very ſolid and effectual: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as any good,
and ſolid argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let it be drawn from any <hi>Topick</hi> whatſoever,
is ſufficient to evince a Truth: and no Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy can, with reaſon, require
more of his Adverſary, than that he ſhould prove ſolidly the
<hi>Theſis,</hi> which he undertakes to defend. <pb n="73" facs="tcp:29434:52"/>Neither
is it neceſſary, That all <hi>Truths</hi> ſhould be evidenced out of
<hi>every place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore it is not <hi>Prudence</hi> to permit; that our
Adverſary ſhould preſcribe us <hi>the manner,</hi> wherein we are to
attack him: it is better to force him to fight <hi>our way.</hi> For though,
perhaps, the way he propoſes unto us, may be <hi>apt enough;</hi> yet another
may be more <hi>advantageous:</hi> and an adverſary may, with more eaſe,
find, in a way wherein he is verſed, <hi>Cavils,</hi> wherewith to elude our
<hi>Arguments,</hi> though never ſo good; then if he be brought into a road,
where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is not acquainted.</p>
            <p>Yet becauſe they may have no occaſion to quarrel with us, as
if we did refuſe to be tried <pb n="74" facs="tcp:29434:53"/>by <hi>Scripture,</hi> we
profeſs, that we are not unwilling to be tried by it. But then it muſt be
with <hi>Theſe Conditions;</hi> which no ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional man can look upon as
abſurd, <hi>viz.</hi> By <hi>True Scripture,</hi> By the <hi>whole Canon of
Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> By the <hi>True Verſions</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and by Scripture
<hi>rightly underſtood.</hi> The ſame may be ſaid of <hi>Councils,</hi>
and <hi>Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have made frequent men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this Diſcourſe, of
<hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental</hi> points of the <hi>True Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> yet we do not
require of our Adverſaries (that which they are loth to do) to exhibit unto
us a <hi>Catalogue</hi> of all ſuch Points. What we require of them is only,
That they grant this point to be <hi>Fundamental,</hi> and
<hi>Eſſential,</hi> to a True Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <pb n="75" facs="tcp:29434:53"/>
               <hi>viz. God
is not the Author of any error, or corruption, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,</hi> or,
<hi>whatſoever God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veals, is true.</hi> And ſure, no Body, who grants
any true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, yea any True Deity, can refuſe to grant This poſition.
For it is certain, that there are ſome Points <hi>determinately
Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental,</hi> and <hi>Eſſential</hi> to a true Religion: and if there
be and ſuch, why not this? The very Foundation of <hi>Divine Faith</hi>
conſiſts in this Principle, <hi>That God does neither deceive, nor is
deceived, in any Thing whatſoever:</hi> and conſequently, that he is not
the Author of any <hi>error,</hi> great or little, and that what ever he
reveals is true. Otherwiſe one might ſay, <hi>Though God has revealed
ſuch a <pb n="76" facs="tcp:29434:54"/>Thing, perhaps it is not ſo, as he has revealed
it:</hi> which doutbleſs would be a manifeſt Blaſphemy. Yea, the
reaſon, why we ought to believe God, <hi>before man,</hi> is, becauſe men
do many times de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and are many times more deceived. But God does never
deceive, nor is deceived.</p>
            <p>We have mentioned alſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times, <hi>Natural</hi> and
<hi>Revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Religion.</hi> By <hi>Natural</hi> Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we underſtand
Thoſe neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary common Principles of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality,</hi> relating to our
duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, our ſelves, and our Neighbour, which <hi>Nature</hi> has
printed in <hi>the hearts</hi> of men; and are uſually ſtiled <hi>The Law
of Nature.</hi> Such are theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. <hi>Do as you would be done by.
Worſhip God. Honour your <pb n="77" facs="tcp:29434:54"/>Parents. Obey your Superiours.
Fly Evil. Do Good,</hi> and ſuch like. <hi>Natural</hi> Religion alſo does
inform us concerning ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Attributes</hi> of God, as that he is
<hi>Supreme Governour of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe,</hi> That he is <hi>not idle</hi> in
the world, That he complies with his <hi>Character,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
that he <hi>rules</hi> and <hi>go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns</hi> the world; That he is
<hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>merciful;</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that he will
<hi>reward</hi> thoſe, who do well, and <hi>puniſh</hi> ſuch as do ill.
By a <hi>revealed</hi> Religion is ſignified a Religion, that contains either
ſome <hi>high Myſteries,</hi> ſeated above the, Sphere of Humane
Reaſon, or ſome <hi>particular manner</hi> of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping God, or ſome
<hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar matters,</hi> wherein we are to <pb n="78" facs="tcp:29434:55"/>obey him;
<hi>freely revealed</hi> unto us by God.</p>
            <p>Now God may manifeſt his will unto men divers ways, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by
<hi>Writings, Words,</hi> or <hi>other Signs,</hi> by <hi>poſitive
Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> or <hi>by Silence</hi> (as men alſo may manifeſt their
will) by <hi>himſelf,</hi> or <hi>by others</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned by him,
whether <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> or <hi>Men:</hi> or he may ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt his will
<hi>partly by Writing,</hi> and <hi>partly in Words;</hi> or <hi>by
Writings,</hi> or <hi>Words</hi> ſo <hi>clear,</hi> that any one may
underſtand them; or ſo <hi>obſcure,</hi> that to underſtand them there
is need of an <hi>Expoſitor.</hi> He may alſo determine by himſelf the
<hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular manner,</hi> wherein he will be worſhipped, and the
<hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular matters,</hi> wherein he will <pb n="79" facs="tcp:29434:55"/>be obeyed; or
he may <hi>aſſign others</hi> to determine them: and though it be Free for
God to chuſe <hi>this,</hi> or <hi>that</hi> way of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning men, yet
ſuppoſing there are men, he muſt needs lay hold of <hi>ſome way,</hi>
or <hi>other,</hi> to manifeſt unto them his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: otherwiſe he
would not comply with this <hi>Character</hi> of being <hi>Governour of the
world:</hi> and conſequently there muſt be ſome Religion <hi>freely
revealed</hi> by God.</p>
            <p>Beſides, out of that common notion of God, aſſented unto by
All <hi>Ens Optimum Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum,</hi> the Beſt of all Things, (though we may
prove the Exiſtency of a Deity by other Notions, agreed upon by the parties)
we may eaſily deduce <pb n="80" facs="tcp:29434:56"/>ſeveral <hi>Attributes</hi> of
God. For God is the Beſt of all Things <hi>in all kind of Perfections:</hi>
Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, as there is one better than another in <hi>Wiſdom, Goodneſs,
Power,</hi> and <hi>other Perfections;</hi> ſo there muſt be ſomething
the Beſt of all, <hi>in All kind of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections;</hi> which we term God.</p>
            <p>If God be the Beſt of all in <hi>Wiſdom, Power,
Goodneſs,</hi> and <hi>in all kind</hi> of perfections, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows that he
is <hi>Free</hi> from <hi>all kind</hi> of <hi>imperfections.</hi> For an
imperfection, in any kind what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, conſiſts in <hi>a defi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iency</hi> from what is beſt in that
kind: and therefore imperfection is commonly defined <hi>Defectus a
ſummo.</hi> Since therefore it is impoſſible, That what is <hi>the Beſt
in all kind</hi> of perfections, <pb n="81" facs="tcp:29434:56"/>ſhould be
<hi>deficient</hi> from being <hi>the Beſt in any kind,</hi> we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,
that God is free from all imperfections whatſoever: and if ſo, then he is
<hi>infinitely perfect</hi> in all kind of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. For all limitation in
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection muſt proceed from <hi>ſome imperfection</hi> in that kind. If
therefore God be free from all imperfection <hi>in what kind ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,</hi> it
neceſſarily follows, that he is <hi>infinitely,</hi> and <hi>without
li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation</hi> perfect <hi>in all kind</hi> of perfections, and
conſequently that he is not conſtituted of Things imperfect: and hence may
be inferred the ſimplicity of the Divine Eſſence.</p>
            <p>Moreover, ſince one thing is better than another, becauſe it
<hi>comes nearer</hi> that, which is <pb n="82" facs="tcp:29434:57"/>the Beſt; and
ſince 'tis impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that any thing ſhould <hi>come nearer</hi> that
which is the Beſt, than what <hi>really,</hi> and <hi>by iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity is the
Beſt;</hi> we conclude, that what is the Beſt, <hi>cannot increaſe;</hi>
and what <hi>cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, is infinite.</hi> For, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is
<hi>finite,</hi> and <hi>limitated,</hi> may increaſe.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding it is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, before we have found
out the True Religion, that we ſhould know any <hi>other Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes</hi> of
God, or any <hi>other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties</hi> of the True Religion, beſides Thoſe
only, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge whereof is preciſely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for the Diſcovery of
the True Religion, and <hi>are admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> by ſuch as we deal with: 
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:29434:57"/>the reſt the True Religion will teach us.</p>
            <p>If one deſire to know, why ſhould one Thing be ſaid to be
better than another, becauſe it <hi>comes nearer what is the beſt,</hi>
rather than becauſe it <hi>goes fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from what is the worſt,</hi> the
reaſon is, becauſe perfection conſiſts in <hi>Poſitives;</hi>
imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in <hi>Negatives:</hi> and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Natural
Order</hi> of Things, <hi>Negatives</hi> are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated by <hi>their
Poſitives,</hi> and not on the contrary: as <hi>Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> is expounded
by <hi>Light,</hi> and not <hi>Light</hi> by <hi>Darkneſs.</hi> So that
<hi>the worſt</hi> is rightly expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the <hi>greateſt
diſtance</hi> from the Beſt: whereas <hi>the Beſt</hi> is explained by
the <hi>Greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction</hi> with that, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains 
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:29434:58"/>all perfection. Yea, if there <hi>muſt</hi> be
ſomething <hi>the worſt</hi> of all Things, why <hi>muſt</hi> there
<hi>not he</hi> ſomething <hi>the Beſt</hi> of All Things? and
conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a True God? which is what we pretended to prove in the Firſt
point.</p>
            <p>And becauſe we deſire to deal fairly, and freely with our
Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries; when we Diſpute with ſuch as profeſs themſelves to be
Chriſtians, we give them leave to aſſign any <hi>ſolid induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
whatſoever, <hi>why they are Chriſtians,</hi> with the Advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
inſinuated, Point the fifth, I do not ask them, <hi>what it is to be
Chriſtians,</hi> but <hi>why they are ſo:</hi> and ſure, no Chriſtian
will be aſhamed to tell any one, what <hi>inducement</hi> he has to be a 
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:29434:58"/>Chriſtian. And to propoſe this queſtion to them, may
contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute much to ground them well in Chriſtian Religion. For there are
Chriſtians, who have ſcarce ever reflected, not only <hi>what it is to be
Chriſtians,</hi> but neither <hi>why they are ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some will tell us, that they are Chriſtians, becauſe they were
<hi>bred,</hi> and <hi>born amongſt Chriſtians,</hi> or becauſe they live
<hi>under a Chriſtian Prince.</hi> But theſe Motives are frivolous. For
though ſuch <hi>circumſtances</hi> have been <hi>the occaſion,</hi> why
many are Chriſtians, yet they cannot be a <hi>prudent Motive,</hi> why
<hi>they are ſo.</hi> For a <hi>Turk,</hi> who is born a <hi>Turk,</hi> and
lives under the <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Government,</hi> has the ſame reaſon to be a
<hi>Turk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:29434:59"/>Others, who have never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected, why they
are Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ask me, what induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I have to be a Chriſtian:
and though this be not to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the queſtion themſelves, but to have me
anſwer for them; yet to ſatisfie them, I may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the forementioned
<hi>miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous propagation,</hi> or ſome other <hi>ſolid Reaſon;</hi>
which being once approved of by them, may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be applied to Catholck
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>Others will ſay, That they are Chriſtians, (and this is the
common anſwer of Proteſtants) becauſe <hi>ſuch Books,</hi> which they
believe to be <hi>the Word of God;</hi> interpreted in <hi>ſuch a
ſenſe,</hi> as they believe they are to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted in, inform them of 
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:29434:59"/>
               <hi>the Divinity</hi> of our Saviour, and of other
<hi>Myſteries</hi> of <hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi> But a <hi>Jew</hi> has the
ſame reaſon to be a <hi>Jew;</hi> becauſe <hi>ſuch Books,</hi> which he
believes to be the <hi>Word of God,</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted <hi>in ſuch a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſe,</hi> as he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves they are to
be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in, tell him, that <hi>Christ is not God,</hi> nor <hi>the
Meſſias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, it cannot be <hi>a good rule</hi> to arrive to the
right ſenſe of Scripture, to interpret it <hi>according to each ones
private reaſon.</hi> For if it were a good rule, who ever ſhould adjuſt
himſelf thereunto, would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret Scripture <hi>in a right ſenſe:</hi>
which is manifeſtly falſe. For Two, who interpret Scripture in
<hi>contradictory ſenſes,</hi> may Both follow <hi>their own private 
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:29434:60"/>reaſon,</hi> as is evident: and yet it is certain, that
either the one, or the other of theſe Two would not interpret Scripture
<hi>in a right ſenſe.</hi> For it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, that <hi>Two
Contradictory ſenſes</hi> ſhould Both be right, and <hi>intended</hi> by
the Holy Ghoſt; who cannot contradict himſelf: and that only is <hi>the
true ſenſe</hi> of Scripture, which was <hi>inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Holy
Ghoſt.</hi> We challenge therefore our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries to produce any ſolid
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements for one to be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, which does not prove that he
ſhould be a Catholick: So that with Truth we may ſay, <hi>No Catholique, No
Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore my main Task in this work, is, to ſhew, that what
proofs are alledged for <hi>Chriſtian <pb n="89" facs="tcp:29434:60"/>Religion,</hi> may
be alledged for <hi>Catholick Religion;</hi> and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence that we have
the <hi>ſame inducements</hi> to be Catholicks, as to be Chriſtians; and
that what <hi>Objections</hi> are made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Catholick Religion, <hi>are,
or may be, made</hi> againſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion: and accordingly that we
have the <hi>ſame Motives</hi> to be No Chriſtians, as to be No Catholicks.
And it would be abſurd to ſay, That we ought not to urge Sectaries <hi>upon
this Topick,</hi> for fear, leſt they ſhould deny Chriſtian Religion to
be true, rather than grant the Truth of Catholick Religion. For in the like
manner they might ſay, That we ought not to urge Sectaries <hi>out of
Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> (or any other Principle <pb n="88" facs="tcp:29434:61"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:29434:61"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:29434:62"/>granted by
them) for ſear, leſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey
ſhould deny Scripture, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her
than aſſent to the Tenets of our Church. By <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi>
I underſtand the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion preached by Chriſt and his Apoſtles:</hi>
which, among other Things, taught as an Article of Faith, that it would
continue to be the true Religion <hi>till the worlds end:</hi> and
conſequently, if it was ever true, it is ſtill true: and ſince,
certainly, it cannot be found but among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, I conclude, that only
among Chriſtians, the true Religion is to be found.</p>
            <p>Neither can I omit here to take notice of a certain kind of men,
who term themſelves <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuoſi,</hi> or <hi>the Wits of the Nation,</hi>
that deny all <hi>matters of Fact,</hi> 
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:29434:62"/>unleſs they
perceive them by their own ſenſes; and admit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but what
<hi>Natural Reaſon</hi> does demonſtrate unto them. So that they deny both
<hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Humane Faith,</hi> all the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of
<hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and all <hi>revealed</hi> Religions. But the
Abſurdity of this opinion is manifeſt. For, as concerning what they
aſſert in reference to <hi>matters of Fact,</hi> we may tell them, that,
according to their Principles, we cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, <hi>That they think what
they ſay,</hi> neither can they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, <hi>That we think what we
ſay.</hi> For their Thoughts to us, and our Thoughts to them, are <hi>matters
of Fact,</hi> ſeated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the pale of the Senſes; <pb n="92" facs="tcp:29434:63"/>and conſequently, if their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples be good, no Body ought <hi>to
treat</hi> with them, nor they with any Body: For no Body ought, in prudence,
to deal with him, whom he can <hi>never believe,</hi> that he thinks what he
ſays. Whence all <hi>Humane Converſation</hi> would be caſt off; which is
againſt the very nature of man. For man is defined, by Philoſophers,
<hi>Animal Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abile.</hi> Yea, the <hi>ſignification</hi> of Words,
Characters, and other arbitrary Signs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we <hi>expound</hi> to others
our Thoughts, do depend upon <hi>Humane Faith,</hi> and upon the perſwaſion
we have, that the <hi>Firſt Inventers,</hi> and <hi>Maſters of
Languages,</hi> intended, that by <pb n="93" facs="tcp:29434:63"/>ſuch words ſuch
Things ſhould be ſignified; and ſo, by deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Humane Faith, they
ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der void <hi>the Inſtruments of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Converſation.</hi> Moreover, no
Servant ought <hi>to obey</hi> their commands, no Body ought <hi>to
condeſcend</hi> to their requeſts. For, no Body, according to <hi>their
Maxims,</hi> can believe that they <hi>intend,</hi> what they ſeem to
<hi>command;</hi> nor that they <hi>deſire</hi> what they <hi>ask,</hi> the
<hi>actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al intentions,</hi> and <hi>deſires</hi> of men, being <hi>matters
of Fact,</hi> which do not fall within <hi>the verge</hi> of our Senſes. And
ſure, no Body ought in reaſon, to obey the commands of a Superiour,
<hi>unleſs he believe,</hi> that he <hi>ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly intends</hi> what he
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; <pb n="94" facs="tcp:29434:64"/>nor <hi>condeſcend</hi> to the requeſt of a
Friend, unleſs <hi>he believes,</hi> that he <hi>deſires</hi> what he
asks.</p>
            <p>Again, ſuch men as Theſe, if they ſtand to their Tenets,
cannot <hi>believe,</hi> that they have <hi>any right,</hi> or <hi>title,</hi>
to the Eſtates, or Prerogatives, which they poſſeſs. For <hi>the
right</hi> to ſuch Eſtates, and Prerogatives, does (as we ſuppoſe)
conſiſt, in that <hi>they deſcend</hi> from ſuch Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, who
<hi>entailed upon their Heirs,</hi> ſuch Lands, or Titles: and according to
<hi>their Maxims</hi> they cannot believe that they <hi>deſcend</hi> from
ſuch Anceſtors. For they never perceived it with <hi>their Senſes.</hi>
Why there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may not one take away <pb n="95" facs="tcp:29434:64"/>their Eſtates,
ſince they can plead no right to them? Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, their actions do
manifeſtly contradict This their aſſertion. For they ſcarce do, or
ſay any thing, great or little, wherein they do not govern themſelves by
the <hi>humane Faith</hi> of ſome thing or other; as they Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves may
eaſily be convinced of, if they will be pleaſed to reflect upon their own
acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>Now concerning what they affirm of <hi>Natural Reaſon,</hi> to
which they will needs ſeem to be ſo much devoted; there can be nothing more
<hi>contrary to Natural Reaſon,</hi> than to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade our ſelves, that
we <hi>ought to believe nothing above <pb n="96" facs="tcp:29434:65"/>it.</hi> For though
<hi>Natural Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> does not demonſtrate unto us <hi>Thoſe
Myſteries,</hi> which are above its reach, yet it does demonſtrate <hi>that
there are ſuch Myſteries.</hi> For, what is more clear to our <hi>Natural
Reaſon,</hi> than that <hi>God does know things above our Natural
Reaſon?</hi> Otherwiſe he would not be <hi>infinitely Wiſe;</hi> as he
would not be <hi>infinitely Powerful,</hi> if he could not do Things <hi>above
our Natural Forces.</hi> If he knows ſuch Myſteries, Natural Reaſon
Demonſtrates, either that he may <hi>reveal</hi> them unto us
<hi>immediately</hi> by himſelf, or that he may <hi>Commiſſion</hi> men
to that intent; otherwiſe he would not be <hi>infinitely Power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful:</hi> 
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:29434:65"/>and that if he does <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal</hi> them unto us, either
by <hi>himſelf,</hi> or <hi>by men,</hi> whom he has
<hi>commiſſioned</hi> to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; we ought to <hi>believe
them;</hi> otherwiſe he would not be of <hi>infinite Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence I conclude, out of the <hi>Principles of Nature,</hi> that
we may be <hi>bound to believe</hi> My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries above the reach of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
Reaſon. For if God does <hi>reveal</hi> them, we are bound to
<hi>believe</hi> them: But he may <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal</hi> them; therefore we may be
<hi>bound to believe</hi> them. Hence it follows, that his conſequence is
Null, (though ſo common in the mouths of the <hi>Virtuoſi</hi>) viz.
<hi>Such a Myſtery is above the reach of Natural Reaſon; Therefore 
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:29434:66"/>we are not not bound</hi> (or <hi>we cannot be bound</hi>)
<hi>to believe it.</hi> Again, if God can <hi>commiſſion</hi> men to preach
unto us <hi>Myſteries, above the reach of our Natural Reaſon,</hi> he may
attend them with ſuch <hi>Marks</hi> and <hi>Signs,</hi> as may evidence unto
ſuch as are concerned therein, that they <hi>are commiſſioned by God unto
them.</hi> For, of what value is a <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> unleſs the
<hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticateneſs</hi> thereof may be made evident? And here I leave
theſe Authors to think with themſelves, what <hi>Signs,</hi> or
<hi>Marks</hi> they would <hi>prudently</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, <hi>to be
perſwaded,</hi> that ſuch men have been <hi>commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned</hi> by God
to preach a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and we engage to evince, <pb n="99" facs="tcp:29434:66"/>That
<hi>ſuch Marks</hi> did concur in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his
<hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other <hi>Preachers</hi> of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,
and Catholick Religion; with this Advertiſement, that they cannot rationally
require a <hi>greater evidence</hi> of Gods commands, to think themſelves
bound to obey them, than of the Kings Commands, in order to ſubmit unto them,
even in matters, wherein their Lives, and Fortunes are concerned: For <hi>the
greater Obligation</hi> of obeying God <hi>before men,</hi> does not
neceſſarily conſiſt in the <hi>greater evidence</hi> of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,
but in the <hi>greater Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of his
Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:29434:67"/>Perhaps, ſome may object, That if we can
find out the <hi>True Revealed</hi> Religion by the <hi>light of Nature,</hi>
without being guided therein, by the <hi>True Religion,</hi> or
<hi>Church,</hi> why may we not find out <hi>All the Articles</hi> of the True
Religion, and Church, without being guided thereby, and without the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious
knowledge thereof, by <hi>the light,</hi> only, of <hi>Natural
Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, that with as much reaſon I might ask our
Adverſaries, why we may not <hi>build the Superſtructures</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
laying <hi>firſt the Foundation,</hi> as we can <hi>lay the Foundation,</hi>
without laying <hi>firſt another</hi> Foundation? or, as we can <hi>go 
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:29434:67"/>by our ſelves</hi> to a Maſter to be taught by him,
why can we not <hi>learn by our ſelves,</hi> what ever ſuch a Maſter can
teach us? or, as by o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r ſelves we
make <hi>appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to the Judges,</hi> conſtituted by the King, to know
<hi>the True Senſe</hi> of the Law, in intricate places; why may we not
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand <hi>the True ſenſe</hi> of thoſe places, without <hi>making
any ſuch application?</hi> Certainly, there is no Body, who does not plainly
ſee, that ſuch queſtions are fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous.</p>
            <p>And ſuch, doubtleſs, is the forementioned queſtion our
Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary propoſes unto us. For the True Church is <hi>the Pillar, and
Foundation of Faith,</hi> the. <hi>Miſtris</hi> of what we are to
<hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> 
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:29434:68"/>and of what we are <hi>to do,</hi> in
order to ſalvation; and <hi>the Judge</hi> in Controverſies of of
<hi>Religion.</hi> Yea, we might ask our Adverſaries, why they might not find
out all <hi>Myſteries of Faith,</hi> without the help of <hi>Scripture,</hi>
as they find out <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> without the previous knowledge
thereof.</p>
            <p>And becauſe our Adverſaries will have Scripture to be the
<hi>Sole Judge</hi> of all Religious Controverſies, let them reflect, that
as, without all queſtion, there would be a <hi>great Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> in a
Kingdom, wherein <hi>every one</hi> muſt decide <hi>all pleas</hi> relating
unto him, by the <hi>writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Law,</hi> underſtood according to his
<hi>private reaſon,</hi> without <pb n="103" facs="tcp:29434:68"/>being <hi>bound</hi> to
ſubmit to the Sentence of any <hi>living Judge,</hi> conſtituted by the
Supreme Governour: So, doubtleſs, there cannot but be a horrid confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
in a Church, where every one is permitted to decide <hi>all Debates</hi> in
Religion by <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> (or the <hi>Written Law</hi> of God)
underſtood according to his <hi>private Reaſon;</hi> without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<hi>bound</hi> to ſubmit to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of any <hi>living Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, the very Conſtitution, and practice of the Church of
<hi>England,</hi> and of other <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Churches,</hi> does evidently
prove, That <hi>Scripture is not the Judge of Controverſies,</hi> nor ſo
<hi>clear,</hi> that any one, who reads it, or hears it read, may, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out 
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:29434:69"/>the help of any <hi>Expoſitor,</hi> or <hi>living
Judge,</hi> manifeſtly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand whatſoever is <hi>neceſſary</hi>
to be <hi>believ'd,</hi> or <hi>done</hi> by him, in order to Salvation: and
that whatſoever any one, by read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Scripture, or hearing it read, does
not <hi>clearly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand,</hi> it is no matter <hi>whether he
underſtands it, or not.</hi> For it is a common practice amongſt the
Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who are perſwaded that their
Church is a True Church, in difficulties that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe about the <hi>true
meaning</hi> of Scriptures, to make their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, (and to <hi>think they
ought</hi> to do ſo) to the Doctors of their Church, to receive from them the
ſolution of ſuch Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties. <pb n="105" facs="tcp:29434:69"/>Now if every one
<hi>by himſelf</hi> clearly underſtands, in Scripture, <hi>whatſoever is
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary</hi> unto him for his ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and whatſoever he does,
not by <hi>himſelf,</hi> clearly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand in Scripture, 'tis <hi>no
matter whether he ever underſtands it, or not,</hi> what need has he to make
his addreſs to the Doctors of his Church, to be inſtructed by them
concerning the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Scriptures? For he needs not their inſtruction,
for what <hi>he underſtands clearly</hi> by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as is manifeſt; nor
for what he does <hi>not clearly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand</hi> by himſelf: For,
accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Doctrine he <hi>needs not</hi> underſtand <hi>ſuch
Things</hi> at all. The ſame may be applied <pb n="106" facs="tcp:29434:70"/>to their
writing ſo many Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes, to prove out of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſeveral <hi>chief
Myſteries</hi> of our Faith. For what need is there of ſuch Writings, if
Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture be <hi>clear</hi> to <hi>every one,</hi> in all Things neceſſary
to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation?</p>
            <p>The Church alſo of <hi>England,</hi> and other Proteſtant
Churches, do Conſtitute <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and <hi>Doctors,</hi> to Preach
unto the People, and to teach them ſuch Things, as are <hi>neceſſary</hi>
unto them, for to ſave their Souls; and vaſt Revenues are allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them
upon this account. Now, if Scripture does teach <hi>all Things</hi>
neceſſary to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>ſo clearly,</hi> that any one, <hi>without
the aſſiſtance</hi> of a <pb n="107" facs="tcp:29434:70"/>Teacher, may manifeſtly
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them; and what he does not manifeſtly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, without
the aſſiſtance of a Teacher, 'tis <hi>no matter, whether he understands
it or not,</hi> why ſhould they Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute Preachers, and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers? or
why ſhould they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign ſuch vaſt Revenues, for an employment, which,
whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he who has it, <hi>does ever exerciſe, or not,</hi> 'tis no matter?
The Practice therefore, and Conſtitution of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church,
and of other Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Churches, does evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evince, That Scripture is
not <hi>ſo clear</hi> that any one, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of an
Expoſitor,</hi> may with eaſe underſtand what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <pb n="108" facs="tcp:29434:71"/>is <hi>neceſſary</hi> in order to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; and that what he
does not underſtand ſo, he never needs to underſtand it at all. And if
Scripture cannot decide clearly, <hi>by it ſelf,</hi> all Debates concerning
matters <hi>neceſſary to Salvation,</hi> certainly <hi>the chief</hi> and
<hi>ultimate Deciſion</hi> of ſuch Debates belongs to the Church: from whom
we may expect a <hi>new Declaration,</hi> and <hi>Definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> (if
occaſion requires) to make <hi>clear</hi> thoſe Things, which before were
<hi>doubtful:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as we can never expect any <hi>new Scripture</hi> to
that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>Beſides, it is certain, that God never intended to write
<hi>ſuch a Scripture,</hi> as No Body <pb n="109" facs="tcp:29434:71"/>ſhould
<hi>depend of another</hi> for the right intelligence thereof: otherwiſe he
would have pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it <hi>in all vulgar Languages,</hi> or in a Language, that
<hi>all ſhould underſtand:</hi> which, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he did not. As therefore
they muſt depend upon the <hi>Skill,</hi> and <hi>Fidelity</hi> of the
<hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlator</hi> in order to have the <hi>True Scripture;</hi> why may
they not depend alſo upon <hi>the honesty,</hi> and <hi>learning</hi> of an
<hi>Expoſitor,</hi> in order to attain <hi>the right Senſe</hi>
thereof?</p>
            <p>Wherefore, unleſs Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants will condemn <hi>the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
Practice,</hi> and even the very <hi>Constitution</hi> of their own Churches,
and render inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant <hi>the main,</hi> and <hi>almoſt only</hi> 
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:29434:72"/>employment of their <hi>Paſtours;</hi> they cannot
believe Scripture to be <hi>ſo clear,</hi> even in <hi>neceſſary
Points,</hi> as they ſeem to make it: eſpecially ſince they are not
ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, that <hi>Scripture it ſelf</hi> does plainly tell them, 2
<hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. that many <hi>hard</hi> and <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure Things</hi> are
contained in Scriptures; wherein the very <hi>Salvation of men</hi> is deeply
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned. And ſince Proteſtants make their addreſs, as daily experience
does teach us, <hi>to their Church,</hi> and <hi>to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> thereof,
in Points contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, 'tis an evident ſign, that they are perſwaded,
that <hi>the voice</hi> of the Church is <hi>clearer</hi> in ſuch points,
than <hi>Scripture.</hi> For no Body can in prudence <pb n="111" facs="tcp:29434:72"/>ſeek out the <hi>right,</hi> and <hi>clear</hi> intelligence, of a
Thing that is obſcure, by what is <hi>as much, or more obſcure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſince moreover, <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral reaſon</hi> does teach us,
that we ought to begin with what <hi>is clear,</hi> to arrive to the right
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence of what <hi>is obſcure,</hi> I conclude, that the <hi>natural
or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> of Things does require, that we ſhould ſeek out the <hi>True
Scripture,</hi> and <hi>True Senſe</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, by <hi>the Church;</hi>
rather than the <hi>True Church</hi> by <hi>the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From what has been ſet down in the progreſs of this
Diſcourſe, 'tis manifeſt, that our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries cannot, with any ſhew
of probability, object againſt us a <pb n="112" facs="tcp:29434:73"/>
               <hi>vicious
Circle,</hi> wherewith they pretend to puzzle many Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Writers; as if
they did prove the <hi>Scripture</hi> by the <hi>Church,</hi> and the
<hi>Church</hi> by the <hi>Scripture.</hi> For though we ſhew <hi>the Truth
of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> and all other <hi>Articles of the Roman</hi> Faith by the
<hi>Truth</hi> of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> yet we ſhew the <hi>Truth of the
Roman</hi> Church, not by the <hi>Scripture,</hi> but by its <hi>miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
propagation;</hi> and its mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous propagation, by the <hi>common
conſent</hi> of our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, by <hi>conſtant Tradition,</hi> and by
<hi>Natural Reaſon.</hi> For our Adverſaries grant, and conſtant
Tradition ſhews, That the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Religion 
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:29434:73"/>is a <hi>hard Religion;</hi> and yet that it has been
propagated <hi>in the manner aboveſaid:</hi> and then <hi>Natural
Reaſon</hi> does teach us, That <hi>ſuch</hi> a propagation of
<hi>ſuch</hi> a Religion could not be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected without the
<hi>particular,</hi> and <hi>miraculous</hi> aſſiſtance of God.</p>
            <p>Some perhaps will deſire to know, what <hi>connexion</hi> we
admit between the <hi>Motives,</hi> and <hi>Inducements,</hi> which we have to
perſwade our ſelves, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is
<hi>True,</hi> and between the <hi>Truth</hi> thereof? or what
<hi>Certainty</hi> we have of the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtency</hi> of ſuch
<hi>Motives</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements?</hi> and whether this Connexion and
Certainty, be <hi>Moral</hi> or <hi>Metaphyſical?</hi> To 
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:29434:74"/>avoid Scholaſtick Nicities, I anſwer (ſuppoſing,
that ſuch as propoſe this Queſtion, do profeſs themſelves
Chriſtians) that the <hi>Connexion</hi> between the <hi>Inducements</hi> we
have to be <hi>Catholicks,</hi> and the <hi>Truth</hi> of <hi>Catholick</hi>
Religion; and the <hi>Certainty</hi> we have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the
<hi>Exiſtency</hi> of ſuch <hi>Inducements;</hi> is <hi>the ſame,</hi> as
the <hi>connexion</hi> between the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements</hi> we have to be
<hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> and the <hi>Truth</hi> of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi>
Religion; and the <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty</hi> concerning the <hi>exiſtency</hi> of
ſuch <hi>Inducements.</hi> So that we have the <hi>ſame kind of
Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty</hi> concerning the Truth of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Church,
and the <hi>particular</hi> Tenets there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <pb n="115" facs="tcp:29434:74"/>as concerning
the <hi>Truth</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, and the <hi>general
Tenets</hi> of Chriſtianity: and the ſame queſtion may be propoſed to
any profeſſour of <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> yea, to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours of
any <hi>revealed</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. So that the difficulty is not <hi>proper</hi>
unto us, but <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> to all ſuch, as allow any <hi>revealed</hi>
Religion; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently they are all <hi>equally</hi> bound to ſolve
it.</p>
            <p>I anſwer again, that the fore-mentioned <hi>Connexion,</hi> and
<hi>Certainty,</hi> is at leaſt <hi>Moral,</hi> (I do not ſay, that it is
not <hi>Metaphyſical</hi>) and ſuch, as to deny, or queſtion it, would be
a <hi>madneſs:</hi> in the ſame <pb n="116" facs="tcp:29434:75"/>manner, as it is
<hi>morally cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> that there have been in the world ſuch men, as
<hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Caeſar, William the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour,</hi> and <hi>Henry the
Eighth,</hi> and that they did ſuch, and ſuch Actions, as are conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
reported by the writers of their Lives, and commonly believed without any
heſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and whoever ſhould call in queſtion any of Theſe Things,
would be look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a Mad man. Wherefore as it would be a madneſs to
ſay, perhaps, there has never been in the world ſuch a man as <hi>William
the Conquerour,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he never was in <hi>England,</hi> perhaps he did
not ſubdue <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by his Arms: So in like <pb n="117" facs="tcp:29434:75"/>manner, it would be a folly to affirm, perhaps, there have never been
in the world ſuch men, as <hi>Chriſt and his Apoſtles,</hi> perhaps they
never <hi>preached Chriſtianity,</hi> perhaps they never <hi>Converted
Nations</hi> from Pagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm to Chriſtianiſm, perhaps they never did any
of Thoſe Miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Actions, which are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recorded of them, and
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly believed by Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>The ſame may be applied to ſeveral Preachers of
<hi>Catholick</hi> Religion. So, doubtleſs, it would be a madneſs to
queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whether there has ever been ſuch a man as Saint <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis
Xaverius,</hi> or whether he ever preached <hi>Catholick</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, 
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:29434:76"/>or ever <hi>converted any people</hi> to it, or whether he
ever did any of <hi>Thoſe ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious</hi> actions, which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
related of him, and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited by Catholicks. For we have at leaſt <hi>as much
evidence,</hi> or the <hi>ſame kind</hi> of evidence, for theſe latter
actions of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> his Apoſtles, and other Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical men, as
for thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer actions of <hi>William the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour, Henry the
Eighth,</hi> or <hi>Julius Caeſar.</hi> Neither were the Miracles of
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> his Apoſtles, and other Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical men, leſs
palpable to ſuch, as were ſtanders by, and from whom they were handed down
to us: nor ſo hard to God, the principal <pb n="119" facs="tcp:29434:76"/>Agent of them,
nor more rare in themſelves, than the famous Exploits of <hi>William the
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour,</hi> and others; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently they are not leſs
cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible.</p>
            <p>Now whoever comes to deny, or queſtion Things <hi>morally
cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> (which to deny, or que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, is a madneſs) he will come
alſo to deny, or queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Things <hi>Metaphyſically cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</hi> For,
what is there, that a <hi>Mad man</hi> will not <hi>deny,</hi> or
<hi>queſtion?</hi> So that, if one will not be Mad, nor Obſtiante,
<hi>Moral Certainty</hi> will be enough to convince him. But if one is
reſolved to be Mad, or Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate; neither <hi>Phyſical,</hi> nor 
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:29434:77"/>
               <hi>Metaphyſical</hi> certainty will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. And
ſo we ſee, that as ſome have denied, or que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned Things <hi>Morally
Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> ſo others have denied, or queſtioned Things
<hi>Phyſical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> or <hi>Metaphyſically certain:</hi> For, there is no
Madneſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Patron. <hi>Nulla fotuitas abſque patrono.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries (ſure) will never confeſs, That
it is <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally certain,</hi> that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the <hi>Roman</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
Religion delivers as an <hi>Article of Faith, is <pb n="121" facs="tcp:29434:77"/>True;</hi> or that the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,
Purgatory,</hi> and the like, are as <hi>certainly true,</hi> as that there has
been ſuch a man as <hi>Henry the Eighth.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it will be enough,
if we can bring Sectaries to grant, that all <hi>the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> of our
Faith are <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally certain.</hi> Yea, if in this Syllogiſm (ſo frequent
in Diſputes concerning the <hi>Reſolution of Faith</hi>) viz.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever God has <pb n="122" facs="tcp:29434:78"/>revealed, is True, and
can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in <hi>any caſe poſſible</hi> be otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>But God has revealed the Myſteries of the <hi>Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, the
Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Real Preſence,</hi> and the other
<hi>Articles</hi> of our Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Myſteries of the <hi>Incarnation,</hi> and
the other <hi>Articles</hi> of our <hi>Faith,</hi> are True, and cannot in
<hi>any caſe poſſible</hi> be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. <pb n="123" facs="tcp:29434:78"/>If (I
ſay) the <hi>Minor</hi> of the fore-mentioned Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſm be granted, or
ſhewn to be, at leaſt <hi>morally cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> it will be a
<hi>madneſs</hi> to deny, or queſtion, not only the <hi>Truth</hi> of the
<hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> of our <hi>Faith;</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo their <hi>incapacity to
be falſe,</hi> in any <hi>caſe</hi> imaginable. And what more, than this,
can <hi>rationally</hi> be required, to evidence the <hi>Truth</hi> of our
Faith, and Religion?</p>
            <p>And, to cloſe up the <pb n="124" facs="tcp:29434:79"/>whole Diſcourſe; I
am confident, that nothing <hi>material</hi> can be objected againſt This
<hi>Method,</hi> which has not been anſwered: though, perhaps, more
<hi>compendiouſly,</hi> than ſome would deſire. Whatever elſe may
occur, contrary unto it, any moderate wit will be able to ſolve.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:29434:79"/>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:29434:80"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. Jane <hi>R. P. D.</hi> HEN. <hi>Epiſc.</hi>
Lond. <hi>à Sac. Dom.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>March 20.
1676./7.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
